<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ's commission-officer: or, The preachers patent cleared, and the peoples plea considered. In a sermon preached before (and now presented to) the associated ministers of Christ, in the county of Sommerset, at the late solemn ordination at Sommerton in said county, June, 9. 1658. By John Norman ...</title>
            <author>Norman, John, 1622-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89720</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1240A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210141</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097874</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097874</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171453</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89720)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171453)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2574:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christ's commission-officer: or, The preachers patent cleared, and the peoples plea considered. In a sermon preached before (and now presented to) the associated ministers of Christ, in the county of Sommerset, at the late solemn ordination at Sommerton in said county, June, 9. 1658. By John Norman ...</title>
                  <author>Norman, John, 1622-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Brewster, at the Crane in Paul's Church yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Epistola dedicatoria" is in Latin.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Dr. Williams's Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ordination sermons --  England --  Sommerton.</term>
               <term>Presbyterian Church --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171453:1"/>
            <p>CHRIST'S Commisſion-Officer: OR, The Preachers Patent CLEARED: AND, THE Peoples plea conſidered. In a Sermon preached before (and now preſented to) the ASSOCIATED Miniſters of Chriſt, in the County of
<hi>Sommerſet,</hi> at a late ſolemn Ordination at <hi>Sommerton</hi> in the ſaid County, <hi>June,</hi> 9. 1658.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Norman,</hi> Min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſter of the Goſpel at
<hi>Bridgwater.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 10.14, 15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>How then ſhall they call on him, in whom they have not believed? and how ſhal they believe in him, of whom they have not heard? and how ſhall they hear with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a preacher?</p>
               <p>And how ſhal they preach except they be ſent? as it is written how beautiful are the feet of them that preach the Goſpel of peace, &amp; bring glad tidings of good things?</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Tim. 1.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I thank Christ Jeſus our Lord who hath enabled me: for that he counted me faithfull, putting me into the Miniſtery</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edward Brewſter,</hi> at the Crane in <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard, 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:171453:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171453:2"/>
            <head>Epiſtola Dedicatoria.</head>
            <head type="sub">Dilectiſſimis, &amp; in Chriſtoper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qùam reverendis Miniſtris Evangelii, apud Somerſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſes <hi>ASSOCIATIS,</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſſimó<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> &amp; pacis &amp; pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis vinculo conjunctis, Gratiam miſericordiam &amp; pacem in Domino.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Patres fratréſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in Chriſto colendiſſimi,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nte oculos ponit conciuncula haec (qualis qualis eſt) omnia illa, quibus nuperrimè praebuiſtis erectas <pb facs="tcp:171453:3"/>aures. Quam acriùs eflagitâ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt non pauci, ut in apricum feram, hanc omnibus &amp; ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis veſtrum perquàm humilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè offero.</p>
            <p>Non eſt quòdlautâ apologiâ ceulongis ambagibus vosfuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lè &amp; nullo cum
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ructu morer. Poſt iteratas à me denuò mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>túmque inficias, vicerunt candem eorum, quibus fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liariſſimè utor, rationes, quae deſiderio Chriſti, coeli, evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelii, ejuſdémque Miniſterii exardere mihi videbantur.</p>
            <p>Pompaticam eloquentiam (ut <hi>Hieronymi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> utar) non ambiit concionator veſter, nec pruritum aurium,
<note n="a" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chryſt. in Tit.</note> ſed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe <pb facs="tcp:171453:3"/>animis:
<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 10 33.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ut cum Apoſtolo loquar, ne inanis reddatur crux Chriſti.
<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſ. in 2 Cor. 11.</note> Oratione itaque preſsâ uſus ſum, non praecultâ
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pienti viro inceſſus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtior con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venit; ita oratio preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa non audax,</hi> Seneca. Ep. 40. <hi>in fine.</hi>
               </note> popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lari, non politâ.
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cujuſcunque orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem vides politam, &amp; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llcitam; ſcito ammum in puſiäis oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupatum in ſcriptis ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>il ſolidum,</hi> Id. Epiſt.
21.</note> Nec minùs de rebus Theologicis dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſemper duxi, quàm de Philoſophicis Cicero: Iſtiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi res dicere ornatè pueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le eſt, planè autem &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuè expedire poſſe, docti &amp; intelligentis viri.
<note n="f" place="margin">Cicero L. 3. <hi>de finibus,</hi> bon.
<hi>&amp;</hi> mal.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Rerum Theologicarum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcatores, potiùs, quam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionatores <pb facs="tcp:171453:4"/>ſunt, qui (ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum <hi>Hieronymum</hi>) exceptis verbis tinnulis atque emendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catis, nihil aliud loquuntur.
<note n="g" place="margin">Hier. Ep.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amil. 56.</note> Liceat itaque ut cum Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolo palàm &amp; ingenuè profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tear, non ſtatuiſſe me quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſcire, niſi Jeſum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum, eúmque crucifixum:
<note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.2.</note> &amp; quicquid ſine hoc nomine fuerit, quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis literatum, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politum, &amp; veridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, non me totum rapuiſſe, ſicut <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinus.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſ. L. 3. ca. 4.</note> Valeant, per me licet, oratorum lenocinia, Platonico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp;
<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Erubiſcat ergò ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbus &amp; infoelix pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, &amp; limeat elatione coecatus, irâ inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, impatien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iae vitio faedatus, ſientiainflatus; cui plus placet ars Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotelis quam ſcientia de Apoſtolis, plus codex Flatonis cuam liber di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinus: quem nulla lectio laetificat, nulla ſapie ntia aediſicat; nullus ſermo ſapit, niſi ſuerit Gram matieè conceptus, Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecticè imaginatus, Rhetoricè purpura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> Aug. li. ſpecul. peccat. e. 6.</note> Peripateti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum <pb facs="tcp:171453:4"/>ſophiſmata: Arma enim militiae noſtrae non carnalia ſunt, ſed divinitùs valida, ad deſtructio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem munitionum:
<note n="l" place="margin">2 Cor. 10.4.</note> Vivus eſt Dei ſermo &amp; efficax<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note> Tota ſcriptura divinitùs eſt inſpirata, eadem<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> utilis ad doctrinam, ad redargutionem, ad correctionem, ad diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplinam in juſtitiâ: Nec ſolummodo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt hominem ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem reddere ad ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutem, verùm etiam hominem Dei cùm <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> tùm
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Seu</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>à Paulo ſcriptum ſit, ut plerique le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ut Complutenſis edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, vim vocabuli</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in ſe inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam habet. Proinde ab Oecumenio ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponitur</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, q. d. <hi>integrè, plenè conſummatè: à</hi> Chryſoſtomo <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i. e. <hi>accurate &amp; exactè instructus,</hi> Jo. Rainold. Theſ. 1. <hi>de S. ſcriptura,</hi> p. 64.</note> 
               <pb facs="tcp:171453:5"/>&amp; perfectum, &amp; ad omne opus bonum perfectè inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum.
<note n="n" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.15, 16, 17. <hi>vide</hi> Andr. Rivet. Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogen. ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In evangelio; en! omnis veritas eſt, &amp; omnis manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatio veritatis, ficut <hi>Origenes.</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Homil. 9. in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od.</note> En!
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Uti Baſilius
<note n="p" place="margin">Contra Eunomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. L. 1. <hi>Ad eun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem modum &amp;</hi> Chryſoſtomus <hi>ſcripturam dicit</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Homil. 13. in 2. ad Corinth.</note> Imò, vel Bellarmino ipſo fatente, En! ſacra ſcriptura regula certiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima, tutiſſimáque eſt
<note n="q" place="margin">De Verbo Dei. I. 1. c. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Ad ſcripturas itaque audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores ubique provoco, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum adoranda eſt plenitudo.
<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Adorò ſcripturae plentudine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> Terr. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve ſ. Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mog.</note> Ad legem &amp; conteſtatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, <pb facs="tcp:171453:5"/>cum Iſaiâ clamito,
<note n="s" place="margin">Iſa. 8.20.</note> Illud ipſum, quod antehàc Conſtantinus, in Synodo Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caenâ, omnibus à me diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientibus ſuadeo: untinam, &amp; addi liceat perſuadeo!
<hi>viz.</hi> ut hoſtilem omnem expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentes contentionem, ex ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis divinitus inſpiratis, ſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem quaeſtionu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> capiamus.
<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theodor. Hiſtor. Ecleſ. l. 1. ca. 7.</note> Audiamus, quid dicit Dominus; non quid dicit Donatus,
<note n="v" place="margin">
                  <hi>glorifica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um eſt nomen meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, dicit Dominus: Audi: dicit Dominus, non di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t Donat us, aut Rogatus, aut Vincentius, aut Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſius, aut Auguſtinus.</hi> Ang. Epiſt. 48. circa med u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> &amp;c. vel hic, vel ille, licèt apprimè eruditus, amicus aut <pb facs="tcp:171453:6"/>pius. Nec audiamus, ut inquit idem <hi>Auguſtinus;</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Contr. Petilianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>de unit.</hi> Ecl. ca. 3.</note> Haec dico, haec dicis; ſed audiamus, haec dicit Dominus. Liceat ejuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem verbis, &amp; fratres alloqui me, aliter hoc in argumento, quod in manibus eſt, ſentien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Sunt certè libri Dominici, quorum authoritati utrique conſentimus, utrique credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, utrique ſervimus, ibi quaeramus eccleſiam, ibi diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutiamus cauſam noſtram. Nolo equidem, (ut ſubjungit ille) humanis documentis, ſed divinisoraculis, eccleſiam, addo &amp; miniſterium, demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri.
<note n="x" place="margin">Idem, ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Illud tamen non diffiteor, <pb facs="tcp:171453:6"/>ſed planè, ut res eſt, haud invitus éxpono; hoc aliquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tò majorem mihi injeciſſe ſcrupulum, utrùm libertas iſta prophetandi, quam adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>târunt fratres, <hi>S.</hi> ſcripturae accommodata fuerit? an po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius abaliena? <hi>ſc.</hi> quod, non modò in Socinianorum
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Docet Paulus rectè id fieripoſſe, unum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quémque munus docendi aggredi, modò ad id aptus ſit, quod aggredi cogitat, vel cupit</hi> Theoph. Nicholaid. <hi>in refut. tract. de miſſ. miniſtrorum. In eandem ſententiam ped<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bus eunt.</hi> Catecheſis Racco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vienſis. c. 2. <hi>Raddecius in not, in librum Smigelecti. Socinus in Tractatude Eccleſiâ. Ejus defenſionem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betis, per</hi> Theoph. Nicholaidem.</note> caſtris, uſitatiſſime eam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnatam habemus, qui ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis parum tribuunt, verum etiam, in Enthuſiaſtarum col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luvie (&amp; ejuſdem farraginis <pb facs="tcp:171453:7"/>homuncionum)
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſt igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſum &amp; Diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dogma Anabaptiſticu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; de homimbus ſine diſcrimine permittendis, functionem eccleſiaſtic am ſuſcipere, &amp; eccleſiam docere.</hi> Hieron. Zanchi. <hi>in quartum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptum.</hi>
               </note> qui ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turas apertè rejiciunt At ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae huic uni ſuffragantur omnes, in hoc unum lubentiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fimè coeuntes.</p>
            <p>Teſtem Deum invoco in animam meam;
<note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.23.</note> me nullis vel iracundiae, vel invidiae igni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis exardeſcere, ob an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciatum Chriſtum, ceu anhelantesſacrorum deſiderio Chriſtianos. Hoc mihi intimè in votis eſt, Dominúmque meſſis animitùs &amp; obnixè rogo, ut operarios in meſſem <pb facs="tcp:171453:7"/>ſuam <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, mittat,
<note n="d" place="margin">Secundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vulgatam interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em</note> emittat,
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dùm</hi> Bez &amp; Ar. Montan.</note> extrudat,
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>ſecundum</hi> E aſmi
<hi>&amp;</hi> Syriac. ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem per Jun. Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel.</note> ceu eijciat,
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>ſic</hi> Hilar.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pud Leig. Cri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ca Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cr. <hi>&amp; ſic ad verbum ſonat, inquit</hi> Beza.</note> Nam meſſis quidem multa, operarii autem auci.
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 9.37, 38. <hi>vid.</hi> Polycarp. Lyſerum ad L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Illud unioè memor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ae infixum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim, quòd Domini ſit extru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere operarios ideoque dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi potius quàm docti eſt,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum intrudere, ceu injicere. Huc ut animum advertatis, in eoque cogitationes altiùs defigere ut placeat, ſuadet haec, quam audiviſtis, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio.</p>
            <p>Rerum ſummas tantùm perſequebar: utpote, qui compendia longis anfracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus anteponenda ſemper ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi. Praeſertim verò, quia ſic <pb facs="tcp:171453:8"/>poſtulabant anguſtiae tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, nec aliud, utplurimum auditorum genii: ut multa in pauca conferam, &amp; omnia (quoad poſſem) quae argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum hoc ſpectant, ut uno quaſi faſce complectar: Nonnulla inſuper adſcripſi: at non ſine deſiderio vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrûm alicujus, multis mihi nominibus pariter &amp; vobis obſervandi, &amp; multimodae literaturae celebritate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corati. Haec ad initium cujuſvis lineae ſic (') inſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nita dedi.</p>
            <p>Me ex aliorum fontibus hortulos hoſce noſtros ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigâſſe, haud inficias eo: <pb facs="tcp:171453:8"/>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim ut arbitror benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, &amp; plenum ingenui pudoris, fateri per quos profeceris.</hi> Plini. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cund, ad Veſpaſian praefat. nat. hiſtor.</note> Nec ſolùm ab alienigenis
<note n="i" place="margin">Joh Gerhard. Loc. Com. Tom. Sext.
<hi>de</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt Eccleſ. ca. 3. ſect. 1. n. 54. &amp;c. r. 64. &amp;c. Fred. Baldvin. Caſ. conſc. l. 4. ca. 4. caſu 1. Joſh. Stegman. Photinianiſm. Diſp. 53. qu. 1 &amp; 2. Hier. Zanchius in quart. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aecept. Chemnit. Loc. Com. de eccleſiâ. Bucanut Loc. Com. 42. qu. 29. <hi>ad</hi> qu. 45. Profeſſ. Leyd. cenſ confeſ. ca. 2. ſect. 2.3. Synopſis pur. Theolog. Diſput. 46. c. 5. Apollonii Conſidera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io quart. controverſ. &amp;c. ca. 5. qu.
3.</note> ſed à noſtratibus
<note n="k" place="margin">Lazar. Seaman <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Gilleſpy Miſcell. queſt. Rutherford peac. plea. ch. 16. qu. 16.
<hi>&amp;</hi> due right of Preſbyt. ch. 5. ſect. 1, 2. Collins vindiciae min. Evangel. <hi>&amp;</hi> vindiciae revindicatae. Hall. Pulpit guarded. Ferreby Lawf. preach Tho. Bali. London Miniſt. Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> divinum Miniſterii E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelii. <hi>Liber vix. ſatis laudatus, &amp; qui de eccleſiâ Anglican â optimè meritus eſt.</hi>
               </note> hoc a gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum teri, eruditioni ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae ſatis compertum eſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171453:9"/>
            <p>Veſtrûm erit, reverendi fratres, aequâ lance trutinare, quid ſit veri, &amp; quid à vero alieni: qui (muſarum dicam? an) ſcripturarum ſacris ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiſſimi eſtis, &amp; politiori li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teraturâ inſtructiſſimi. Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid boni occurrit, aut veri, illud Dei eſſe, palam profite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or: ſin aliquid mali, vel falſi, (quod me prorſus latet) hoc planè noſtrî eſt.
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Omnia bona mea, nec ſunt purè bona, nec purèmea; omnia mala mea, &amp; ſunt purè mala, &amp; purè mea.</hi> Hugo.</note> Hîc, primùm operam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, ut quantum omnino potui, cum ſcripturis loquar,
<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sic inſtruit Zep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perus, de arte ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendi &amp; audiendi conciones Sacr.</hi> l. 3. c. 3.</note> &amp; nec fallar in eis, nec fallam ex eis <pb facs="tcp:171453:9"/>
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sic adprecatur Auguſtinus. Sint caſtae deliciae meae ſcripturae tuae: nec fallar in eis, nec fallam ex eis,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſ. Lib. 11. c. 2.</note> Penes vos ſit judicium, his de rebus: quibuſcum, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quàm grati in vos animi, &amp; permagni affectus (licèt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiguum) teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium, libellus hic deponitur.</p>
            <p>Gratâ memoriâ amores, mores, res veſtras omnes proſequor. Grata mihi ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in mentem occurrit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia veſtra, grata comitas, grati conventus, grataconſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo &amp; colloquia. Eruditam, quam apud vos frequentiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus obſervavi pietatem, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardeſcentes preces, efferveſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centem zelum, exoptatam <pb facs="tcp:171453:10"/>ſubmiſſionem, exantlatos la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bores, &amp; emeritas <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> laudes nulla unquam apud me deleat (nec delebit) oblivio. At temperabit ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, quamvis nunquam tacebunt affectus.
<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ipſe me citiùs quàm vos obliviſcar: etſi unquam ſermo tacebit, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetur affectus.</hi> Ambroſ. <hi>de</hi> Gratiano <hi>&amp;</hi> Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiniano.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Pernavigate, chariſſimi fratres, &amp; verbi &amp; vitae velis expanſis, ſecundiori ſpiritus afflatu fruituri, potiaminíque votis, amico ſidere, amicis ſanctis, ad Dei gloriam, Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolorum gravamen, eccleſiae pacem, &amp; eccleſiaſticorum proſpera, frementibus licèt <pb facs="tcp:171453:10"/>&amp; frendentibus Satanâ, ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſectatoribus.</p>
            <p>Non eſt, quòd noſtrûm quivis, Jonae inſtar,
<note n="p" place="margin">Jon. 1.5, 6.</note> in tot tantíſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> eccleſiarum procel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, ignorationis, ignaviae, intemperantiae, aut ingenii vafri ſomno ſit conſopitus. Officio honeſtati ſumus. Hoc unicum,
<note n="q" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.1. <hi>ad</hi> 6. <hi>Epiſcopus eſt nomen quod plus oneris, quàm honoris ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficat.</hi> Polyd. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil.</note> quas ſcintillas admoveret? quos ſtimulos adji<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret? ut Chriſti propugnatores, &amp; carnis expugnatores noſmet comprobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Optimè cedet laboranti.
<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quot labores ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritati nunc exhibes, tot etiamremunera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s pignora, intra ſpei tuae cubiculum clauſum tenes.</hi> Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor. Moral.</note> Nec ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt quo minùs in <pb facs="tcp:171453:11"/>lautiora provehantur dona, ipſiſſimo uſu, &amp; docendo promoveamur doctrinâ.
<note n="s" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quò in plures diffunditur, eò redundantior manat, &amp; in ſuum fontem recurrit. In ſe enim refluit ubertas prudentiae, &amp; quò pluribus fluxerit, eò exercitius fit omne, quod remanet.</hi> Ambroſ. Offic.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Quod ad me ſpectat, cum praefecto Pharaoni à poculis, peccata mea recordaturus ſum hodie;
<note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 41.9.</note> ingenuéque cum Ambroſiorecog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſco:
<note n="v" place="margin">Offic. c. 1. <hi>Lice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at &amp; cum eodem inſuper adſcribere —&amp; quantumlibet quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> profecerit, nemo eſt: qui doceri non egeat, dum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat.</hi> Ibid.</note> quòd pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ùs docere inciperem; quàm diſcere: Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendum igitur mihi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſimul &amp; docendum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eſt. Nec profiteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb facs="tcp:171453:11"/>piget, Auguſtini verbis
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ego ex eorum numero me eſſe profiteor; qui ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt profictendo, &amp; ſcribendo proficiunt</hi> Epiſt. 7.</note> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rùmmutatis, exeorumnumero meeſſe, qui doce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tproficiendo, &amp; docendo proficiunt
<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mutuò iſta fiunt ut homines dum do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceant, diſcant.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca Epiſt. 7.</note> &amp; in hoc gaudeo (uti Seneca) ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid diſcere, ut doce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am: nec me ulla res delectabit, licet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imia ſit &amp; ſalutaris, quam mihi uni ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turus ſum.
<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem,</hi> Epiſt. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Veneror equidem inventa ſapientiae:
<note n="z" place="margin">Senec. Epiſt. 65.</note> &amp; facilè eorum ſententiae accedo, qui judicâ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, nemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> unqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habuiſſe doctrinam inmicum, niſi ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantem. Ideoque de indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriâ, hâc in re, aliquantiſper verſata ſuit haecconcio, nequis <pb facs="tcp:171453:12"/>auditorum à veritatis trami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, hâc ex parte, deflectat. Illud verò planè meminiſſe, &amp; penitâ mente reconditum vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem; aliud eſſe erudiri de ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatibus Jeſu Chriſti, aliud edoceri de eo, ficut veritas eſt in Jeſu
<note n="a" place="margin">Ehpeſ. 4.20, 21. <hi>Nunquid Domine Deus veritatis, quiſquis novit iſta, ipſe placet tibi? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faelix enim homo, qui ſcit omnia illa, te autem neſcit: Beatus autem qui ſcit, etiam ſi illa neſciat. Quiverò &amp; te &amp; illa novit, non propter illa beatior ſed propter teſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lùm beatus eſt. &amp;c.</hi> Aug. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ. L. 5. c. 4</note>. Poteſt quis peritus eſſe, imò praedicator,
<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.27</note> tamen periturus
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quid prodeſt peruum eſſe, &amp; periturum!</hi> Aug. Confeſ. L. 11. C. 2.</note>. Nec ſic immorandum eſſe ſcientiis judico, ut poſt habitae ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſcripturae
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quid prodeſt in muda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere doctrinis &amp; marceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinis? Caduca ſequi fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta, &amp; coelestia faſtidire myſteria?</hi> Iſidor. <hi>de li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris</hi> Gentil.</note>; nec ipſiſſimis ſcripturis, poſt-habito ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu
<pb facs="tcp:171453:12"/>
               <note n="e" place="margin">—<hi>O Domine perfice me, &amp; revela mihi eas.</hi> Aug. Conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. L. 11. ca. 2 — <hi>Agnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus gratiam, quae facit prodeſſe doctrinam, quae gratia ſi deſit, videmus etiam ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe doctrinam.</hi> Idem Epiſt. 107.</note>. Animalis enim homo non percipit, quae ſunt ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Dei, in ſcripturis niſi, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenti ejuſdem ſpiritus adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento
<note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14. Pſal. 119.18.</note>, cujus inſpiratione, exaratae ſunt ſcripturae
<note n="g" place="margin">2 Tim. 3 16.</note>.</p>
            <p>Sed manum de tabulâ. Ut veritati &amp; vobis proſperè ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedant omnia, obnixè peto. Adunitis veſtris conſiliis, conatibus, &amp; caeptis omnibus, fauſta laetáque omnia pecor. Ut vivat Chriſtus; valeat <pb facs="tcp:171453:13"/>cauſa ejus, vigeat concordia, nec diutius vacillent Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani: ut revaleſcat, quae eſt ſecundùm pacem, diſciplina, &amp; radices altiores agat, quae eſt ſecundùm pietatem, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrina; iterum atque iterum, inſtat oratio</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Devinctiſſimi vobis fratris</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>ac in Domino conſervi</hi> JOH. NORMAN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:171453:13"/>
            <head>To the plain, eſpecially the pious READERS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ext to the glory of God my Saviour, the good of your ſouls, was it that ſubdued me; (who had elſ been ſtill deaf to all intreaties of friends and fellow-labourers) to let you ſee this from the Preſs, which others (&amp; probably, ſom of you) heard from the Pulpit. The ſame God, who perfects ſtrength in weakneſs, that ſo far proſpered it when it was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the ear, make it now likewiſe powerfull upon the heart, when it is delivered to the eye. If either ſin ſhal be reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <pb facs="tcp:171453:14"/>by it, or the ſaints refreſhed, or the ſaucineſs of ſeducers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked, or the ſervice of our Saviour regularly advanced, the ſpeaker hath his end, the ſermon its errand. Some things are now ſet before you, more than were then ſpoken: Some things which I did not then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, eſpecially for further cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of objections; others, which I could not then deliver, for the fuller carrying on of the application. Both are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thus marked (') at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of each line. The reſt you have welnigh in the ſame words which you then heard, as near as my notes and memory could
<pb facs="tcp:171453:14"/>ſuggeſt it, onely ſome things now and then may be herein de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered leſs contractly: eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the uſes. Before you peruſe, pray. Man may open the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to your underſtandings, but God alone can open your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings to the Scriptures
<note n="a" place="margin">Luk. 24.45. Pſ. 119.18.</note>. As you peruſe, pauſe a while, and conſider; conferring the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall texts and truths, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring ſpirituall things with ſpiritual. If you wil notmeditate upon, &amp; ſearch God's Word, I ſhall never marvail, if you miſtake or ſlight mens writings. Having peruſed, put things to an iſſue; as in the preſence of God, judging your ſelves that <pb facs="tcp:171453:15"/>you be not judged. Do you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude upon the whole, that ſuch as undertake to be teachers ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily in the Church without ordination, are but toyling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their own corruption? Oh! let conſcience be put off by you, while it is ready to put to you ſuch queſtions as theſe. Is it a ſin for this man to preach, and can it bee ſafe for thee to hear him? Canthy attendance be wel, &amp; his act ſo ill? Shal his guilt increaſe by it, and wil thine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe? Doth heviolate an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, and invade an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice ſo ſacred in the Goſpel? And durſt thou beſide thy conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence at this attempt, bring it all <pb facs="tcp:171453:15"/>the countenanee, whereto thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany will amount? Could the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his heart make him a preacher, unleſs thy preſence with others, (probably the more for thee) did maintain him hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? O my ſoul! Shall I that hope f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r heaven, harden him in that ſin, for which he muſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repentance, howl in hell for ever? Is this to reprove? or doth it not approve this work of darkneſs, to give it the reſpect of my obſervance in the open light? Shall I not knowingly hereby communicate in his ſin? and how can I have comfort thence for my own ſoul? Hath God prohibited him to preach? <pb facs="tcp:171453:16"/>and how can I have a precept to hear? or hope to profit by hearing him? Where have I
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> promiſe that I ſhall, or how ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I pray in faith, that I may reap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any ſoul-advantage by him? e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, while I run my ſelf upon ſuch a tentation, inſtead of reclaiming him from his tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion? Nay, hear the Word of the Lord: I ſent them not, nor commanded them: therefore they ſhal not profit this people at all, ſaith the Lord, <hi>Jer. 23.32.</hi> Hearken not to the words of ſuch Prophets; for I have not ſent them, ſaith the Lord, <hi>Jer. 27.14.15.</hi> &amp; <hi>23.16.</hi> with
<hi>21.</hi> Reader had'ſt thou ſeen the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <pb facs="tcp:171453:16"/>tears, that were bled forth at the eyes; or heard the paſſionate throws, that were breathed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orth from the hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s by one of thoſe
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts of Chriſt that were now ſolemnly ſet apart [That ever he ſhould preach ſo many ſermons without a ſolemn ſending forth! and to which he could ſee no promiſe of ſucceſſe! &amp;c.] It could not but have made ſome impreſſion upon thy heart, as it did upon mine and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. I ſhall detain thee no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but to deliver my own ſoul, in the words of Zealous, and Studious <hi>Baxter</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Firſt ſheet for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,
<hi>p.</hi> 14.</note>. Christian Reader, as ever thou wouldſt be
<hi>ſanctified, confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſaved,</hi> hold faſt to <hi>Chriſt, Scripture, Miniſtry,</hi> and <hi>Spirit;</hi> and that in the
<hi>Church</hi> &amp; <hi>Communion of Saints;</hi> and abhor the thoughts of
<hi>ſeparating each from other.</hi> And to declare my ſenſe of the ſame truth, in the ſame terms, with holy and humble Dr. <hi>Sibbs</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſtle to the Reader be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> P. Bayns <hi>on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he</hi> Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fianst,</note>, now in heaven. I ſpeak <pb facs="tcp:171453:17"/>not as if way were to be given to <hi>Vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> lawleſs, licentious, liberty
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> propheſying; that every one, as ſoon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he is big of ſome new conceit, ſhon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bring forth his abortive monſter: F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thus the pillars of Chriſtian fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> would ſoon be ſhaken, &amp; the Church
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God, which is an houſe of order, wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> become a Babel, an houſe of confuſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> The doleful iſſues of which pretende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> liberty we ſee in <hi>Polonia, Tranſylva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> and in Countries neerer hand Reader, the doleful iſſues which we ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>England,</hi> let us ſigh over, &amp; ſprea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> before the Lord, in whom Ireſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy ſoul-friend, JOHN NORMAN</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171453:17"/>
            <head>CHRIST'S <hi>Commiſſion-Officer:</hi> OR, AN Ordination-Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Timothie 2.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And the things that thou haſt heard of me, among many witneſſes, the ſame commit thou to faithfull men, who ſhall be able to teach others alſo.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe two Epiſtles of <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> and the next to
<hi>Titus;</hi> what are they, but <hi>Paul</hi>'s Directory for the regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar continuance, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend carriage of the Goſpel-Miniſtry? Two things he infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h upon principally: The inveſtitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <pb n="2" facs="tcp:171453:18"/>of ſome with the Office of Miniſters, the imployment of ſuch in this Office. How and on whom <hi>Timothy</hi> and
<hi>Titus</hi> ſhall confer it, and how themſelves and thoſe ſhould carry themſelves in it: what was their part for delegating men to the Miniſtry, and what muſt be their own and others part and demeanour in the Miniſtry. Theſe things are very accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately and abundantly interſperſed.</p>
            <p>Lo, it is not enough (without further preface) that
<hi>Timothy</hi> in theſe, and <hi>Titus</hi> in the next Epiſtle look how they do comport themſelvs, but they muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this ſacred truſt to others; the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the Miniſtry is ſo eminent: and this with the beſt-ſighted caution, and moſt ſtudious circumſpection, the nature of the Miniſtry is likewiſe ſo excellent. This, this beloved &amp; much reverenced; which is the end of your preſent conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is <hi>Paul's</hi> charge, and muſt be <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie's</hi> care in this verſe. <hi>The things that thou haſt heard of me among many witneſſes, the ſame commit thou, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Four things wuſt be here briefly enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into. 1. The matters or things which are to bee committed. 2. The manner <pb n="3" facs="tcp:171453:18"/>how? 3. The man by whom. 4. The men to whom theſe things are to bee committed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, what are the things which <hi>Timothy</hi> muſt commit?
<hi>Paul</hi> tells him, <hi>The things that thou haſt heard of me, the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thou.</hi> But whether thoſe which hee had heard from
<hi>Paul</hi> publickly and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly in his preaching, or more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly thoſe at his own <hi>ordination,</hi> when hee was put into the Miniſtry by
<hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note n="a)" place="margin">2 Tim. 1.6.</note> together with the Presbytery,
<note n="b)" place="margin">1 Tim. 4.14.</note> be the chief or only things in our Apoſtles eye, it is not expreſſed: The enſuing words beſpeak the laſt (at leaſt partly, if not) principally intended.
<hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy it is plain, is not only charged in theſe Epiſtles with teaching others, but with or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining teachers: And no doubt, but with committing unto others the Office to teach, he is to commit ſuch Goſpel-truths by teaching, as ſhall be of beſt, and moſt inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viency, to their holy and happy conduct, throughout the difficulties, and diſcharge of their office of Teachers. A point of eaſie obſervation, and eminent uſe, which could not probably be omitted at the Apoſtles Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of</hi> Timothy, <hi>that hath obtained <pb n="2" facs="tcp:171453:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:171453:19"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:171453:20"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:171453:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:171453:21"/>well-nigh an univerſall concurrence, at eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ordination ſince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, but how muſt <hi>Timothy</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit theſe things?
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. It would be little other than a waſt of precious time, and of your patience, to produce the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Scriptures in which, or purpoſes to which, this word is uſed. There are but two ſenſes (I humbly conceive) that can with any probability bee tendered here: <hi>viz.</hi> Either that <hi>Timothy</hi> commit theſe things to others in way of doctrine only, by teaching and opening theſe things to them; or in way of delegation alſo; and ſpeciall truſt, as the word is often uſed;
<note n="c)" place="margin">1 Tim. 1 18. <hi>cum</hi> 2 Tim. 1.14. Lu. 12 48. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>The ophyla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus hoc diſcrimen conſtituit in verbis</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Illud accipit de miraculoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doni, boc verò de Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nillerio. vi de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>plura a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Bezam ad loc. &amp; Leigh. Crit. ſac. ad ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum.</hi>
               </note> truſting theſe things with them as Officers, who are to teach others, and muſt therefore be a depoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and treaſure-houſe of divine truths for others. This latter ſenſe,
<hi>which emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently taketh in the committing of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to teach,</hi> is that which to me ſeems, moſt eſpecially in our Apoſtles deſign and purpoſe, for theſe two reaſons. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, 1. This moſt openly correſponds, not only to the ſubject in hand, but to the ſcope of the whole: both Epiſtles being to direct <hi>Timothy,</hi> eſpecially about
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171453:21"/>publick Ordinances and Officers: how he ſhall Ordain Officers, and how theſe and himſelf ſhall order the affairs of their Office. 2. This hath the moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, if not the only countenance from the Characters given us, of the men to whom <hi>Timothy</hi> is to commit theſe things which are immediately ſubjoined. For if <hi>Timothy</hi> were to commit theſe things to them only, in way of doctrinal teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; what need or uſe was there, of ſo ſevere a reſtriction, or of ſuch ſpeciall qualifications, as we read added? <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men, able to teach others alſo:</hi> which <hi>Gilleſpy</hi> in his <hi>Miſcellany Queſtions, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins</hi> in his <hi>Vindiciae,</hi> and the <hi>London Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> in their <hi>Jus Divinum Miniſterii Evangelici,</hi> do very well obſerve. No doubt, but as to the doctrinall teaching of theſe things, <hi>Timothy</hi> was no leſs a debtor, than was <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Barbarian,</hi> as well as Greek; to the unlearned, as well as learned; both to the wiſe, and to the unwiſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.14. So that <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> is to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit
<hi>theſe things,</hi> more than in way, of doctrine only: He is to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them in way of delegation alſo, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch <hi>faithfull men, as ſhall be able to <pb n="6" facs="tcp:171453:22"/>teach others:</hi> which cannot rationally be underſtood, of other than <hi>publick and authoritative teaching;</hi> if either 1. the quality of the men, or 2. the contents and aim of theſe Epiſtles, which concern publick tranfactions in the Church, eſpecially publick teachers: or if 3. the command it ſelf be duly weighed: fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch as are to teach but privately, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from grounds of charity only, need n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch commitment of theſe things t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them; nor needs it that there be ſuch choyce of men: this being every ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and womans duty,
<hi>Heb</hi> 5.12. <hi>Nor ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any thing be juſtly impleaded, from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles uſe of the future tenſe,</hi> [who ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> able to teach others alſo] <hi>for though tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they ſhal be able to teachothers, be neceſſari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> antecedent to the commitment of the Office<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſenſu phyſico, <hi>i. e. that they ſhal have abi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lities to teach: yet it followeth, the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Office,</hi> ſenſu morali, i. e. <hi>tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they ſhall uſe ſuch abilities ordinarily, or b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> able to teach others, acceptably, and lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: remembring ſtill that old, honeſt, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> veceived principle.</hi> Illud tantum poſſumu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> quod jure poſſumus. <hi>We are able to do n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more, than we are able in Law, or may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:171453:22"/>lawfully. And thus our text aptly corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponds to that of the ſame Apoſtle,</hi> Rom. 10. verſ. 15. How ſhall they preach except they be ſent? <hi>i. e.</hi> how ſhall they preach warrantably?
<hi>Abilities they muſt have before ſending, but ſending veſts them with authority.</hi> So that the words ſpeak as much in effect as this; Doth
<hi>Timothy</hi> know ſuch as are faithfull and fit, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to teach others; <hi>he muſt commit theſe things to them, as Truſtees for others.</hi> Doth he find any ſo qualified for the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to teach, hee muſt leave them Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned to this Office: Are they quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with fidelity and ability, <hi>Timothy</hi> muſt commit to them a furniture of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriy.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, but how muſt <hi>Timothy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit theſe things,</hi> this Office to them? What! he only? he, and none but hee? No, we never find the Miniſtry commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to any, by a ſingle perſon; but ſtill it is done by ſeverall in ſociety. <hi>We al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways read of more than one concurring to it, and never remember leſs than two:</hi> And thoſe are no leſs than were
<hi>Paul</hi> &amp; <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas, Act.</hi> 14.23. The Twelve are aſſociates in it, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.2, 3, 6. and it is the joint act
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171453:23"/>of how many teachers and Prophets? <hi>Act.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3. The ſeat and ſubject of this power, is not a Presbyter; but the Presbytery,
1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. Can we ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally think, that <hi>Paul</hi> doth require
<hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> to commit the Miniſtry to others, ſo as recedes from, and hath no conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtency with the practice of <hi>Paul</hi> in the ſame caſe, upon <hi>Timothy</hi> himſelf? Well, and who of us doth not remember, that <hi>Timothy</hi> received his Commiſſion, no ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the laying on of <hi>Paul's</hi> hands, but of the Presbytery likewiſe? 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1,
6. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. True 'tis, that <hi>Titus</hi> is to Ordain Elders, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, City by City, where the Churches were planted, and their condition called for it; but with this <hi>proviſo,</hi> as
<hi>Paul</hi> had appointed him. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. And who can think, that
<hi>Paul's</hi> appointments, and <hi>Paul's</hi> actions ſhould ſo little accord, or ſo much inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fere? that <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould order either
<hi>Titus</hi> there, or <hi>Timothy</hi> here, to do that ſingly by himſelf, which <hi>Paul</hi> an Apoſtle never did (if I may not ſay, never durſt) but in ſociety? It is granted, that this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand did concern
<hi>Timothy</hi> eminently, and ſignally above others; but not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſively, <pb n="9" facs="tcp:171453:23"/>ſo as to ſhut out all others. It muſt be done by others likewiſe, though it be directed to, and is to be directed by him eſpecially, as one that had an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and ſpeciall truſt, about the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of this and all other Church affairs being by office an Evangeliſt. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5.</p>
            <p>Fourthly. Yet once more; to whom muſt <hi>Timothy</hi> commit this truſt, theſe things in way of office? What? to all the Congregation? No: There muſt be ſome to be taught, as well as others ſent forth to teach. What then? to any of whatever qualification? Nor this. They muſt be at leaſt men <hi>of a good life, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men;</hi> yea, and men of <hi>good learning too, that ſhall be able to teach others alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The text thus opened, the truth is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, which I ſhall at this time take up, or obſerve from it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> Thoſe that are authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively from Chriſt, in his Church, to teach others, muſt have that Office com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them, as well as bee qualified for that Office.</p>
            <p>How orient <hi>(me thinks)</hi> is this obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in all its truths from the text! Lo, 1. Some there muſt be in the Church,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171453:24"/>who are authoritatively from Chriſt to teach others. But then 2. That there may be ſuch in the Church who are from Chriſt to teach authoritatively, they muſt have the Office committed to them by ſome
<hi>Timothy.</hi> Yet 3. <hi>Timothy</hi> may not give Commiſſion to this Office, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he find qualifications for this Office. <hi>Timothy</hi> may not dare to confer authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on any, without due cognizance firſt had, both of their fidelity and ability. Well, 4. Hath God qualified any with fidelity and ability; yet though they are able to teach others, they may not acceptably teach others in the ſenſe mentioned, (unleſſe for proof of thoſe abilities) untill <hi>Timothy</hi> hath from God committed to them authority likewiſe.</p>
            <p>But to lead you further abroad. Give me leave to open and offer to you, theſe five things, and thereto lend me I beſeech you, your moſt ſtrict and ſerious atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 1. There muſt bee ſome in the Church who are by Office from Chriſt authoritatively to teach others. 2. They muſt be qualified for this Office. 3. They muſt have this Office co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to them.
4. How it muſt be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted. And 5. Why <pb n="11" facs="tcp:171453:24"/>it muſt be committed to them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, there are to be ſome in the Church, who are by Office authoritative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from Chriſt to teach others. I ſay by Office; but this not civil, but ſpiritual. Officers wee are, not in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, but in the Church, to which Chriſt hath promiſed. I will alſo make thy Officers peace, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.17. Thus bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and beloved, we may with
<hi>Paul</hi> magnifie our Office.
<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 11.13.</note> An Office the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry is, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. Yea, ſuch is the Deaconſhip,
<hi>ver.</hi> 10.13. and therefore this much more, which as to your want, and its worth doth ſo much tranſcend that, as the Apoſtles intimate
<hi>Act.</hi> 6.2. What leſſe than this? [that it is an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice] doth
<hi>Paul</hi> aſſert of his own Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry? <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.13. or aſſure the Saints of ours? when he tells them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.4. That as we have many members in one <hi>body naturall,</hi> and all members have not the ſame <hi>Office;</hi> ſo 'tis in the <hi>body myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> too,
<hi>ver.</hi> 5.6. wherein Deacons, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, Teachers, and Rulers be in diſtinct Office, as the 7. and 8. <hi>verſes</hi> import. So that Preachers are by Office diſtinct from and dignified above the people. Are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171453:25"/>all Teachers ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.29. It is no more poſſible that all be Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters or Teachers in the body ſpiritual, than that all be Magiſtrates in the body civill; or that all be Officers in the body military; or that all the members be eye or tongue, in the body naturall: If <hi>all</hi> may be <hi>Teachers,</hi> where are the others to be <hi>taught?</hi> of whom this Text tells us. Need I mention the practice under the Law, the Prophecies then touching the Goſpel, or the precedents left us in the times of the Goſpel? He that runs may read, a conſtant diſcretion <hi>between the Prieſts and people then, between Pastor and people now, between the members of the Church, and the Miniſters of the Church in both. To the Law and to the Teſtimony.</hi> And here how eminent a difference hath the Holy Ghoſt made! Miniſters of the Church are to be
<hi>overſeers,</hi> members of the Church to be <hi>overſeen, Acts</hi>
20.28. Theſe are ſet <hi>under,</hi> thoſe ſaid to be <hi>over</hi> them in the Lord, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12. Theſe are to ſubmit, thoſe to preſide and rule, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7, 17. Briefly, theſe to bee
<hi>taught,</hi> the other to <hi>teach, Galat.</hi> 6. <hi>ver.</hi> 6.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:171453:25"/>
            <p>Yea, teach we muſt not only with <hi>aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duity,</hi> but with <hi>authority.</hi> With authority I ſay, not <hi>magiſterial</hi> indeed, as if we were <hi>Lords over the Church;</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. That is interdicted: <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.42. but <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtertall,</hi> as <hi>over the Church in the Lord;</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12. this is incouraged.
<hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. Far! far be it, that we ſhould preach up ſuch an authority, as if we had <hi>dominion over your faith!</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi>
1.24. No, all the authority which we plead for, is the <hi>diſpenſation (not domination) committed to us, for the good of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi> 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 9.17. The authority which the Lord hath given us, is for your
<hi>edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> and not for your <hi>deſtruction,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi>
10.8. And with this reſtriction, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this reſpect, let me tell you; that we are to teach, and exhort, and rebuke, not only <hi>with authority, but with all authority,</hi> Tit. 2.15. and there is not that holy Miniſter, but may ſpeak wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h holy
<hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah,</hi> according to his meaſure: <hi>Truly I am full of power by the ſpirit of the Lord, &amp; of judgment, and of might to declare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Jacob his tranſgreſſion, &amp; unto Iſrael his ſin Mic.</hi> 3.8. True it is, that all Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members ought to be teachers of others.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171453:26"/>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12. But this private and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative: Chriſt hath therefore over and above, appointed in his Church ſuch tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing likewiſe, as may be <hi>publick and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritative.</hi> i.e. <hi>that there be ſuch teachers, who are by power and authority derived from him to them, publickly to open and apply the Scriptures, for the converſion and edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſouls; as in his ſtead, and not only in private,</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'Where yet, ſuch in teaching are properly enough ſaid to preach, though it be in a <hi>private houſe. Act.</hi> 5.42. or but to one <hi>particular perſon; Act.</hi> 8.35.</q> it being not ſimply an act of
<q rend="margQuotes">'charity in them, but an act of authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which it cannot be ſaid to be in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</q> 
               <hi>Charitative teaching</hi> which ſhould be <hi>every mans work,</hi> too ſoon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh
<hi>no mans work.</hi> And therefore, Chriſt hath ordained, that there be pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar officers for <hi>authoritative teaching,</hi> who are to give themſelvs wholly to it, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.15. and muſt not only be able to teach, as the Text ſpeaks; but muſt be apt to teach, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.24. and abide in teaching. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16. And unto theſe teachers, all people are bound to attend, as thoſe that teach <hi>not only by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171453:26"/>but by authority derived from Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Luke
12.16. Indeed, <hi>how ſhall they hear without a preacher ſent?</hi> Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
10.14, 15</p>
            <p>Think you, that ſuch teachers are now ceaſed; and that this office was of no longer continuance, than the firſt age or century of the Church? Oh! Where are your conſiderations of the everlaſting Kingdome of Chriſt?
<note n="a)" place="margin">Iſ. 9.6.7. Lu. 1.33.</note> of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches perpetual exiſtencies?
<note n="b)" place="margin">Mat. 16.18. Heb. 12.27, 28.</note> and of her continued preſſing exigencies?
<note n="c)" place="margin">Rom. 10.14. Eph. 4.12.13, 14.</note> or of our deareſt Chriſts ends by, and enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gements to the Miniſtry?
<note n="d)" place="margin">Mat. 28.19, 20. Lu. 24.46, 47.</note> Did a Kingdom ever ſtand without Officers? Did the Church ever ſubſiſt without a Miniſtry and Ordinances? Or hath Chriſt ſaid that ſhe ever ſhould, on this ſide glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? Nay hath he not rather told us, that the word of the Lord endureth for ever? and that this is the word, which by the Goſpell is preached to you? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.24.25. Beloved, did not Chriſt aſſure his Chriſtian Churches by prophecy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Old Teſtament, of giving them teachers by office, without limiting it to this, or that Century or age? <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.15 Nay rather, letting us underſtand, that he will have ſuch continued, even after <pb n="16" facs="tcp:171453:27"/>the Jews are called, if you compare that verſ with the 14, 16, 17. ver. Or <hi>Jer.</hi>
23.3.4. &amp;c. or <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.20, 21. Beſides, When Chriſt had actually ſent forth firſt the Twelve, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.1. and after that the Seventy, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.1. and again enlarged their Commiſſion,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. doth not he aſcertain his preſence with them, e're he parted from the earth, alway, <hi>to the end of the world, ver.</hi> 20. which could not intend themſelves onely, but muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude their ſucceſſors,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quamvis quoad mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum &amp; gradum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarii Miniſtri nullos habent ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſores, quoad ipſam ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men eſſentiam admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrationis, eodem of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio funguntur Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri Ordinarii verſus Eccleſiam, quo extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarii olim funge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur</hi> Ameſ. Medu. Theol. lib. 1. ca. 35. n. 4.</note> who-e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver are, according to his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, bid go teach and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize: For the Diſciples, where are they and the Apoſtles? do they live for ever? Again, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſcended up on high, did not our Lord Chriſt give gifts unto men? and thus, not only ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and ſome Evangeliſts; but ſom Paſtors and Teachers, for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the Body of Chriſt: ends of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued and conſtant obſervation, need, and uſe. But till when, ſhall theſe Paſtors
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171453:27"/>and teachers endure? and how long ſhal the Church enjoy them? Till wee are all come in, or into
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>quod ſcitè expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit Syrus interpres, quaſi Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſit,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. maj. ad. Loc.</note> the unity of the faith, and of the knowledg of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4 8, 11, 12, 13. Shall I add to all this? how Chriſt hath particularly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, for the inveſtiture of fit and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men with this Office, in his ſeverall Churches, in theſe two Epiſtles to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> and in the next to <hi>Titus;</hi> and how hee will have theſe Commandments, inviolably and impartially <hi>kept until his appearing,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.21, 22. chap 6.14. <hi>Readers, if you can believe, that there is no more need of labourers for husbandry,</hi> [1 Cor. 3.9.]
<hi>or of ſeedſmen, or reapers for harveſt,</hi> [2 Cor. 9.11. Luk.
10.2.] <hi>or of builders for houſes,</hi> [1 Cor. 3.9, 10.]
<q rend="margQuotes">"or of ſome to plant and water for gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and orchards; [1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.] then, and not till then, may you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the Church ſhall have no more need of Miniſters by office: for thus the Scriptures mentioned, expreſs our neceſſities of them to us. Sure I am, if Church-members may be ſtill called <pb n="18" facs="tcp:171453:28"/>the Sons and Daughters of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. Such Miniſters may be likewiſe called the Spirituall Fathers, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. the ſpirituall nurſes that feed and nouriſh them, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7. 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 3.2. and are the ſtewards, that when grown up, are to give them their portion of meat in due ſeaſon, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.42. In a word, if men had need ſtill to be believers, they have ſtill need of Miniſters, by whom ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3 6. and if ye are ſtill Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims and ſtrangers, 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 2.11. how ye can want ſuch Officers as are called guides, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7. and the light of the Word, <hi>Mat</hi> 5.14. I muſt profeſs, I ſee not; farewell the Office-Miniſters of Chriſt in
<hi>England,</hi> and farewell the chariots and horſmen of <hi>England,</hi>
2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.12.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> Secondly, thoſe that are by Office au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatively from Chriſt to teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, muſt be qualified for this Office, before they have it committed to them. This is a true ſaying indeed, if a man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Office of a Biſhop; (which term in Scripture phraſe, beſpeaketh no more then a Presbyter or Miniſter
<note n="a)" place="margin">Tit. 1.5. with 7. Phil. 1.1. Act. 20.17. with 28. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a word e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where elſe re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Biſhop by our tranſlators.</note> many of <pb n="19" facs="tcp:171453:28"/>our Engliſh Biſhops
<hi>i. e.</hi> Prelates them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves being judges
<note n="b)" place="margin">A.B. Whitgift againſt Cartwright, p.
383. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelm in 1 Tim. 3. B. Bridges of the Princes Supremacy p. 255. B. Bilſon againſt Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries lib. 1. p. 318. ſee B. Jewel againſt Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Def of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. par. 2. ch. 3. diviſ. &amp; chap 9. diviſ. 1. &amp; B. Morton Cathol A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. par. 1. ch. 33.</note> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth a good work, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. But muſt not this bee acknowledged a true ſaying likewiſe, that who and what the man is that deſireth it;
[how able? how apt &amp;c?] ſhould be firſt conſidered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he be Commiſſioned, or ſet apart unto it? Elſe what mean thoſe numerous chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters, which <hi>Timothy</hi> hath given him in charge, that are continued to the eight verſe, and whereof <hi>Titus</hi> is re-minded likewiſe, by the ſame Apoſtle, when he appoints him to ordain Elders in every City, at leaſt of <hi>Creet, Tit.</hi> 1.5. <hi>ad</hi> 13. Or what means elſe that notable and no leſs dreadfull charge? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.
<hi>ver.</hi> 21.22. I charge thee before God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the Elect Angels, that thou obſerve theſe things, without preferring one before another, doing nothing by partiality. Lay hands ſuddenly on no man, neither be partaker of other mens ſins, keep thy ſelf pure. Ah my brethren! <hi>Church-work is chary <pb n="20" facs="tcp:171453:29"/>work. Lay we on hands ſuddenly, and we lay them on ſinfully.</hi> And to be ſure, we ſhall partake of other mens ſins, if we ſhall ſo little prize their, our own, &amp; other mens ſouls, which any thing below the blood of him that was God,
<note place="margin">Act. 20.28 1 Pet. 1.18.19.</note> is too ſmal to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe? Come ſirs, <hi>who is the faithful and wiſe ſteward?</hi> him ſhall the Lord make ruler over his houſhold, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.42. And ſhall we, who are the Lords by Office, and muſt account to the Lord for our Office; ſhall we make them <hi>rulers,</hi> who will <hi>manifeſtly ruine more than rule</hi> the houſhold of Faith? Can wee keep our ſelves
<hi>pure,</hi> and yet be careleſs of confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſuch a <hi>power,</hi> ſuch an <hi>honour,</hi> as the <hi>Miniſtry is? it hath a power to bind to, &amp; looſ from hell; A power to open and ſhut heaven, Mat.</hi> 16.19. and an <hi>honour</hi> abſtractly ſo called, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4. that doth not onely ſpeak us to be Embaſſadours for Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. but Angels rather than men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. <hi>C.</hi> 2. <hi>O beloved! who is ſufficient for theſe things? Surely none are in regard of adequation, and alas! how few in regard of acceptation?</hi> But what though we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find men <hi>equall</hi> to the Office, ſhal we forget, that men ſhould bee able for the <pb n="21" facs="tcp:171453:29"/>Office?
<note n="*" place="margin">See more uſe 2 ſect 1</note> Surely,
<hi>the bold precipitancies of men uncalled upon this Office, and the bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy preceleratings of men unqualified into this Office, are abominations never enough to be bewailed before the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Thoſe that are authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively from Chriſt to teach others in his Church, muſt not only be quallified for this Office, but muſt have the Office com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them. Hear the Apoſtle; <hi>How ſhall they preach except they be ſent? Rom.</hi> 10.15. How ſhall they ſaith he?
<hi>Nay they do; and this how often! how open! and God ſent them not, ſay the godly: Yea I have not ſent theſe Prophets, yet they ran; I have not ſpoken to them, yet they propheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſaith God himſelf. Jer.</hi>
23.21. True, they do it <hi>wickedly;</hi> but how ſhall they do it
<hi>warrantably?</hi> How ſhal they preach except they be ſent?
<hi>i.e.</hi> with the <hi>appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of God's Law;</hi> they may eaſily
<hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture upon it from their own luſt,</hi> How ſhall they preach either with ſucceſs and countenance from him? or without ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ſawcy preſumption in them? How dareth he perform the Heralds Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, to proclaim war and peace in the conſcience, who was never put into the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171453:30"/>Office, nor can produce an Herald's pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent? This is the Metaphor, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> How ſhall they preach as God's
<hi>Herald's?</hi> Lo Chriſtians! <hi>beſide meetneſs for the Office, an Herald of God, a Miniſter, muſt have miſſion: ſuitableneſs</hi> to the Office is not enough without <hi>ſending.</hi> Nay, are you not told, in the ſame ſtrains of reaſon and Rhetorick; that there is as great a neceſſity of ſending, that we bee preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as was and is of preachers, that you be hearers? or of hearing, that you bee believers? or of believing, if you expect an anſwer to, and the acceptation of your prayers? So high our Apoſtle car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth it, if you look back upon the 13, and 14.
<hi>verſes.</hi> Such an holy concatena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion maketh he of all theſe.
<q rend="margQuotes">'So that you cannot bear us in hand, with the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Socinian, that there remains no more a neceſſity of ſuch ſending, ſince the Apoſtles ceaſed: for that (ſay they)
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Oſtorod</hi> in <hi>Inſtit.</hi> c. 42. <hi>Th. Nicholaid. in deſenſ. Tract.</hi> ſo <hi>cui de Eccl.</hi> c. 1. <hi>Schmaltz. in reſert. Theſ.</hi> D <hi>Frantz. per.</hi> 2.
<hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put.</hi> 4.</note> theſe were to preach a new doctrine, which we now are not. For with what faithfulneſs can this be ſaid, <hi>in regard ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of hearers,</hi> the interrogations all running in ſo clear and conſtant a ſtream? 'Tis as much ſaid, How ſhall <pb n="23" facs="tcp:171453:30"/> they hear without a Preacher? and how ſhall they believe in him of whom they have not heard? &amp;c as how ſhal they preach except they be ſent? <hi>Or in regard of the holy Apoſtles?</hi> who aſſure us, that they preached no other things, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe which <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> did ſay ſhould come. <hi>Act.</hi> 26.22. <hi>Chap.</hi> 24.14. <hi>Chap.</hi>
28.23. And not only, as they paſſed to and fro, did they ordain Elders in every Church, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed a conſtant courſe for Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on likewiſe, as the Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and
<hi>Titus</hi> witneſſe. Nor can you ſay, that they are ſent of God, who are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gifted. For as it is not ſaid; how ſhall they preach except they be gifted? but, <hi>except they be ſent; and that as watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and meſſengers,</hi> as the next words import out of the Prophet
<hi>Iſaiah</hi> 52.7.8. So, the Scripture never ſaith that gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is ſending, but ſuppoſeth that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily before this; &amp; diſtinctly ſpeaks of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> of the abilities to preach or prophecy, and authority to preach or prophecy,of mens
<hi>ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble qualifications for it,</hi> and <hi>ſending forth with commiſſions for it.</hi> Witneſs <hi>Ezek.</hi> 2.2, <pb n="24" facs="tcp:171453:31"/>3. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 6.7.8, 9. <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.7, 9. <hi>Joh.</hi>
20.21, 22. And what though it be true; that ſending imports many times, Gods commmanding men to go forth to the work of the Miniſtry? yet, as no gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted brother can ſhew us any ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from God, ſo it's obſervable; that the Scripture never mentions any as ſent forth to preach or propheſie, but the ſame perſons were always, either mediately or immediately, appointed of God unto the Office. Witneſſe <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1 8, 9.
<hi>Jer.</hi> 1.5, 7. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10, 1, 5, 16.
<hi>Mar.</hi> 3, 14. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.6 <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.10, &amp;c. An immediate miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to this Office there are no pious men will boaſt they have; or if they did, there are no prudent men will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they have, till, they ſee it atteſted with a power of miracles; Nor is there any promiſe whereupon any ſhould hope for it. So that I cannot but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude upon the whole:</q> 
               <hi>That no man can now preach Ordinarily and orderly, without Ordination, or being ſent forth of God me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately. He ſins in preaching that is not thus ſent forth with power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to draw the proof of this propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition out into more pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ticulars. Bee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171453:31"/>pleaſed to obſerve the expreſſe precepts, eminent precedents, and evident pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, wherewith God hath counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced it, and the elegant properties &amp; titles wherewith Miniſters are clothed, which beſpeak it.</p>
            <p>Sect. 1. See the <hi>expreſſe precepts of God for it</hi> (to wave the implicit only.
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.22. Rom. 10.15. Heb. 5.4.</note>) Behold as they miniſtred to the Lord; and faſted, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.2. the holy Ghoſt ſaid <hi>Separate me Barnabas and Saul for the work whereunto I have called them.</hi> And accordingly, the Prophets and teachers, mentioned ver. 1. When they had faſted and prayed, and laid their hands onthem, they ſent them away, ver. 3. Obſerve, Chriſtians. God had ſuited them to the work. God had ſupplied them with fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yet theſe muſt ſeparate them to the work, and ſend them forth. And why this ſeparating, think we, of ſuch extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary officers; if not to ſanctifie, as it were, and ſeall an <hi>Imprimatur</hi> upon the ordinary rule? It is granted, that
<hi>Pauls Apoſtleſhip was not of men, neither by man, but by Jeſus Chriſt, and God the Father who raiſed him from the dead,</hi> Gal. 1.1. That he was firſt <hi>immediately</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned hereunto by Jeſus Chriſt, as it <pb n="26" facs="tcp:171453:32"/>was declared to <hi>Ananias, Act.</hi>
9.15. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> if the holy Ghoſt will have one ſo <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly &amp; immediately called,</hi> to paſs thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> common road, before the ordinary exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of his office among the Gentiles; who of us then, may plead immunity from it, or proudly take another by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>path? Though
<hi>God had every way quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Paul and Barnabas</hi> for the miniſtery, though <hi>God had eminently called them</hi> to the miniſtry, yet that theſe Prophets and Teachers do <hi>externally commiſſion,</hi> or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate them to the Miniſtry likewiſe, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>evidently the command of the Holy Ghoſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Let me preſent you next with that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of God by
<hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Titus, Ch.</hi> 1.5.—And <hi>ordain Elders in every City, as I had appointed thee.</hi> What Elders meaneth he? <hi>By age?</hi> No, time, as one ſaith,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Collins vindic. Miniſt, Evang. qu.</hi> 2.</note>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>&amp;c.</note> not
<hi>Titus</hi> muſt make theſe. What Elders then? Flders by
<hi>Office,</hi> as the words enſuing clear it; and thoſe, <hi>not in the ſtate, but among and over the Saints:</hi> Biſhops, or overſeeers, who are to hold faſt the faithfull word, <hi>verſe</hi> 7, 9. Now thus, there is <hi>ſomewhat ſuppoſed</hi> in theſe words, that there ſhould be Elders in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry City, where the Churches were <pb n="27" facs="tcp:171453:32"/>eſtabliſhed; and <hi>ſomwhat propoſed</hi> how the Churches muſt be ſupplyed with El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. How ſo? <hi>Titus</hi> muſt ordain them,
<hi>Ordain Elders in every City. They are not Elders by Office then, till Ordination.</hi> But what is this? muſt <hi>Titus</hi> qualifie them for this Office? and is this all, which is intended by it? No; this was God's part, and is to be preſuppoſed on their part, e're <hi>Titus</hi> may put forth any ſuch act to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, as Ordination is; if you conſult the following verſes 6. <hi>ad</hi> 10. <hi>Titus</hi> may <hi>diſcuſs</hi> and ventilate their gifts and qualifications, but God onely can <hi>derive</hi> and furniſh.
<note n="d)" place="margin">Iſ. 1.17. 1 Cor. 12.6</note> That which
<hi>Titus</hi> hath in charge is to Ordain, to confer the Office of Elders,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: and in that notion is the word uſed, not only by profane Authors frequently,
<note n="b)" place="margin">Sic apud Demoſthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Xenoph. &amp; Herodia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occurrunt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; ſimiliter</note> but by the Apoſtles, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whom we may appoint over this buſineſs, as our tranſlators render it: This how did they? but by prayer, and laying their hands on them, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. and ſo putting them into the Office of Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons? beſides if gifts, if qualifications could have made them Elders, of what need or uſe was there of ſuch an order <pb n="28" facs="tcp:171453:33"/>from <hi>Paul?</hi> or of Ordination by
<hi>Titu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> for thus they had been Elders already before and without either; if but
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> charactered, as the next verſes do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe. And if ſo, how is <hi>Titus</hi> require<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to Ordain ſuch? and why reſtrained to Ordain ſuch onely? So obvious is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that beſide a competency of ability of their part, there muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment or Ordination on
<hi>Titus</hi>'s par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> likewiſe; or they are not to be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged Elders. So expreſs are the precepts of God for it.</p>
            <p>Sect. 4. <hi>And what eminent precedents find we among the godly for it?</hi> Surely no man taketh this honour to himſelf, but he that is called of God, <hi>Heb</hi> 5.4. True, <hi>many a man doth</hi> de facto,
<hi>but not any man doth (i. e. ought)</hi> de jure. Not <hi>Aaron</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, nor any of the Prieſts after his order:
<q rend="margQuotes">'They were ſeparated from among the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to their Office;
<note n="*" place="margin">Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 8.14 &amp; 2.6. &amp; 1 50. Exo.
28.1. 2 Chro. 29.11.</note> which was not only <hi>to offer ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice unto God,</hi> but to <hi>open the ſtatutes of God,</hi> &amp; teach in
<hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note n="b)" place="margin">Deut. 33 10 Levit. 10.11. 2 Chr.
17.18.9.</note> the work now of every Goſpel Miniſter.</q> So, nor did the Apoſtle and high-Prieſt of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion Chriſt Jeſus; He alſo glorified not <pb n="29" facs="tcp:171453:33"/>himſelf to be made an
<hi>high-Prieſt;</hi> but he that ſaid unto him, <hi>Thou art my ſon, to day have I begotten thee, Heb.</hi> 5.5. What, did he glorifie himſelf to be made a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet then?</hi> Neither. The Spirit of the Lord God (ſaith he) is upon mee, and hath <hi>anointed</hi> mee to <hi>preach good tidings, &amp;c. Iſa.</hi> 61.1. <hi>i.e.</hi> anointed me not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with <hi>abilities,</hi> but with <hi>authority.</hi> Hee was a Prophet of the <hi>Lord's</hi> raiſing up, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.22. <hi>If I honour my ſelf</hi> (ſaith hee in his Miniſtry) <hi>my honour is nothing; it is my Father that honoureth me, Joh.</hi> 8.54. It was the Father <hi>ſanctified</hi> and <hi>ſent</hi> him into the world, about his Miniſteriall concernments, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.36. and
<hi>ſealed</hi> him his Commiſſion, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.27. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,
<hi>as my Father ſent me, even ſo ſend I you;</hi> ſaith he to his Diſciples, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.21. Ah beloved! <hi>Self-Miniſters</hi> then
<hi>are none of our Saviours Miniſters. His Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters can ſay; he made us, and not wee our ſelves. And with</hi> Paul, 1 Tim. 1.12. <hi>I thank Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, who hath ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled me, for that he counted mee faithfull, putting me into the Miniſtry.</hi> Obſerve, He doth not thank him onely for his <hi>ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blings</hi> for the Miniſtry, but for his
<hi>inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiture <pb n="30" facs="tcp:171453:34"/>with</hi> the Miniſtry; not onely
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his <hi>promptneſs for it, but for putting him i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it.</hi> So diſtinct a notion did the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Prophets keep, of their <hi>qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fications</hi> for the Miniſtry, <hi>which made the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> apt to teach;</hi> and of their
<hi>commiſſion</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be Miniſters <hi>which gave them authority
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> teach.</hi> Lo, as they were
<hi>allowed of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be put in truſt with the Goſpel,</hi> (ſo they te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us) they ſpake 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4. and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the glorious <hi>Goſpel of God wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> committed</hi> to them, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.11. Did theſe holy men of God think it enough, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they were <hi>able to preach?</hi> Nay, but this was it they choſe rather to inſiſt upon, that they were (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelf) <hi>appointed preachers,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.11. True it is, they durſt not but manifeſt his word through preaching, but then it was <hi>committed to them according to the commandment of God our Saviour, Tit.</hi> 1.3. And therefore how often have wee them, both in the Propheſies of the Old Teſtament,
<note n="g)" place="margin">Jer. 1.5, 7, 17. Ezek. 1.3. &amp; 2.3, 7,
8. Hoſ. 1.1, 2, &amp;c.</note> and in the Prefaces to moſt of the Epiſtles
<note n="h)" place="margin">Rom. 1.1. 1 Cor. 1.1. Jam. 1.1. 1 Pet.
1.1. &amp;c.</note> in the New Teſtament, inſiſting upon, and juſtifying of their <hi>callings</hi> to bee Prophets and Apoſtles? Beloved, hear <pb n="31" facs="tcp:171453:34"/>you any of them pleading, that qualifications are a ſufficient Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion? or for a freedome of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying by un-officed Prophets? (pardon the in congruence of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion) or, becauſe God hath fitted a man with parts and abilities, that hee needs no other furniture of power or authority, to exerciſe and exert them? Rather; do you not hear and read them, <hi>diſtinctly propounding, and directly proving their Commiſſion, over and above their qualifications?</hi> Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you, <hi>that God did not onely bring them gifts, but bid them go,</hi> Iſai. Chap. 6. verſe. 9. Amos Chap. 7. verſe 15. Jeremiah Chap. 1. verſe 7. Ezekiel Chap. 3. verſe 1, 4, 11. That God <hi>ſanctified</hi> them for, that GOD <hi>ſent</hi> them forth to, and God <hi>ſet</hi> them in their Miniſteriall work and Office, <hi>Jeremiah Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſe</hi>
5.7.10. <hi>Ezek. Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſe</hi> 3.4. <hi>&amp;c. Not onely had they diſpoſitions and gifts for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating the Goſpel, but a diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the Goſpel was committed to them,</hi> 1 <hi>Corinth. Chap.</hi> 9. <hi>ver.</hi> 17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.7. O my brethren! are we compaſſed about <pb n="32" facs="tcp:171453:35"/>with ſo great a cloud of witneſſes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall wee yet think the commitment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Miniſtry needleſſe or uſeleſſe?
<q rend="margQuotes">'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> can wee ſuffer our ſelves to bee put o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with ſo poor a pretext as this? That a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theſe inſtances from the Apoſtles an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prophets do not ariſe to the Ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on now practiſed, by the interventio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of men, and impoſition of the hands o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Presbytery. For who ſeeth not, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they fully reach to evince the
<hi>neceſſity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a commiſſioning to the Office, beſide quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications for the Office of Miniſters;</hi> which is the point now before us? And it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more then manifeſt, that the <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate ways of committing men to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry are now ceaſed, and a mediate way from God inſtead thereof, commanded</hi> which is written as with a Sun beam, in the Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy</hi> and
<hi>Titus:</hi> unleſs you will <hi>break</hi> with God, and theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents among the godly, <hi>by putting your ſelves into the Miniſtry, whereas they were put into it of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. Theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances will in effect and virtue <hi>bind</hi> you to the Ordination now practiſed; if it be the only way now preſcribed, and leſt us of Jeſus Chriſt: Of which hereafter.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:171453:35"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. Thirdly, <hi>ſee yet further the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident preſcriptions,</hi> which are given forth for putting men into Miniſtry, by our Lord Jeſus? and theſe how numerous; that they fill up a good part of three E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles. Beloved, conſider I beſeech you. <hi>Why ſhould the conferring of the Miniſtry be ſo preſſingly directed to</hi> Timothy
<hi>and</hi> Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus? <hi>why ſhould the call of men to, and their qualifications for the Miniſtry be ſo plainly differenced? Why ſhould the committers, and they committed to it, be ſo particularly diſtinguiſhed?</hi> If gifts, with a deſire to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe them, were ſufficient? or the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn committing of this Office, were but ſuper-erogatory and ſuperfluous? Would the bleſſed Spirit of wiſedom have ſpentit ſelf in ſuperfluites, think we? Is there no more ſet before us, but <hi>who are to be Miniſters?</hi> and how they are to act
<hi>in their Miniſtry?</hi> Hath not the ſame ſpirit ſet before us, their <hi>appointment and putting into the Ministry</hi> likewiſe? Ay; and this how <hi>articulately!</hi> By what <hi>men?</hi> in what <hi>manner?</hi> after what <hi>matters previous?</hi> and by what <hi>means preſent?</hi> Who are to be <hi>Ordainers?</hi> who, and how they are to be <hi>Ordained?</hi> what is <hi>pre re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired <pb n="34" facs="tcp:171453:36"/>to it?</hi> what to be
<hi>performed in it?</hi> and what the <hi>product and iſſue of it?</hi> Read elſe but 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>Chap</hi> and 1 <hi>Chap.</hi> of
<hi>Titus.</hi> Sirs, why this waſt, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more were no other ordination to the Office of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, but what gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, and our own, or others deſires to u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e them make? O you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ſtand in the way and ſee, and ask for the old paths, where is the good way that we may walk therein, muſt you not ſay of
<hi>this? This</hi> is it, wherein God hath been alway wont to meet, and give miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to his ſervants: <hi>either immediately by inveſtiture of them with the Office from himſelf,</hi> as our Lord was pleaſed to ſend forth firſt the Twelve, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.1. and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſeventy, <hi>Luk</hi>
10 1. <hi>Or elſe mediately, by the interpoſition of his own Officers,</hi> as <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mothy</hi> is directed to do in this <hi>verſe.</hi> We: doth <hi>Matthias Apoſtolize?</hi> not till Chriſt <hi>appoints</hi> him, <hi>Act.</hi> 1. Do
<hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas?</hi> not
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll our Saviour
<hi>authorize</hi> them, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.17. <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.2. Hath every Church its <hi>Elders,</hi> that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the word and doctrine? Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> and
<hi>Barnabas</hi> firſt <hi>Ordain</hi> them, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. Is it the order of Chriſt that there be <hi>Elders</hi> in every City? but withall
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:171453:36"/>that <hi>Titus Ordain</hi> them, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. Hath
<hi>Timothy</hi> the gift or Office of an Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt? but not without the
<hi>laying on of Pauls hands,</hi> and of the Presbytery like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe? 2
<hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4. There muſt be ſuch who are by
<hi>calling to teach others?</hi> but <hi>Timothy</hi> muſt <hi>commit this truſt</hi> to them for others, as in the Text. Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, why are theſe things written? and for whom think we? Are they not for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the world are come? Doubtleſſe, <hi>whatſoever things were written aforetime, were writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for our learning, that we through patience and comfort of the Scriptures might have hope, Rom.</hi> 15.4. Ah Sirs! may we dare to reject this word of Chriſt? or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move to another way of our own or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers contriving? either <hi>frame new ways of committing the Miniſtry</hi> (I mean)? or elſe <hi>frowardly deny the continuance of the Miniſtry,</hi> as too many do? Nay can you ſo forget the <hi>Commandment</hi> of Chriſt, and his <hi>Covenant</hi> with his Miniſters, which hee calls upon us ſo affectionately to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, as a thing of moſt happy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke, <hi>Mat.</hi>
28.19.20 <hi>Go teach, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:171453:37"/>Lo, <hi>I am with you alway,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>all days,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>to the end of the world.</hi> Which cannot bee reſtrained to the end of that age; as the pregnancy and propriety of this phraſe,
<note n="*" place="margin">See it learnedly Vindicated &amp; opened
<hi>Jus divin. Mini. Eva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> par. 1. c. 2. p. 27. <hi>ad</hi> 31
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and the parallel uſage of it by this ſame Evangeliſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.40. <hi>(m) Chap.</hi> 24.3. <hi>(n) (beſides the precedent paſſage which is not all your days, but all days)</hi> do plentifully evince. Or have you ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten that command by <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy?</hi> I give thee charge in the ſight of God, who quickneth all things, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt Jeſus, who before <hi>Pontius Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> witneſſed a good confeſſion: That thou <hi>keep this commandment without ſpot, unrebukeable, untill the appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> What commandment intends he? I humbly conceive, with
<hi>Beza</hi> and others
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſt. Homil</hi> 18. <hi>Ambr. Lyra Gorra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel à Lavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Diodat. &amp; Engl. Annotat. ad</hi> ver. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> this
<hi>complex command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment contained in, and carried along thorow the whole Epiſtle;</hi> unto which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle quickens him with ſix arguments.
<note n="(p" place="margin">Dickſon ad loc.</note> And thus it
<hi>eminently</hi> taketh in that (well-nigh) paralell charge, <hi>Chap.</hi>
5. <hi>ver.</hi> 21.22. which <hi>includeth</hi> the confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Miniſteriall Office, as doth <pb n="37" facs="tcp:171453:37"/>the third <hi>Chapter.</hi> And what though this Commandment could not bee fulfilled till the coming of Chriſt by <hi>Timothy himſelf?</hi> yet might it bee by <hi>Timothie's ſucceſſors:</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'Who are clearly concerned to attend this charge of the Apoſtle, as addreſſed <hi>to them in Timothy;</hi> the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and intent of the Scriptures being not only for the preſent men and times, but for all that ſucceed or follow
<note n="q)" place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pſa. 119.152. Lu. 16.16, 17. Rev. 22.19</note> And verily, 1. if there ſhall ſtill be till his coming, both
<hi>ſinners</hi> to be <hi>begotten un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt;</hi> and to be brought into his Church; and if there be <hi>Saints</hi> to bee <hi>brought forward,</hi> and to bee <hi>built up in communion with Chriſt and his Church;</hi> and if there be <hi>ſouls</hi> to bee <hi>ſanctified and ſaved,</hi> until the time of his appearance. (which who doubts that believes any thing?) And 2. if our Lord Chriſt hath <hi>onely ordinarily</hi> annexed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, to beſtow theſe great bleſſings <hi>by a Miniſtery ſent,</hi> as it is cleer he hath, <hi>Rom. Chap.</hi> 10. <hi>verſe,</hi>
14, 15. <hi>Epheſians Chapt.</hi> 4. <hi>verſe</hi> 11, 12, 13. <hi>Having by this onely (uſually) brought about the addition of ſinners to his Church and to himſelf,</hi> Acts the ſecond Chapter, and the 41. and 47. verſes, and Chap. 11. <pb n="38" facs="tcp:171453:38"/>verſ. 24. <hi>the converſion of ſouls to, and their confirmation in and with himſelf,</hi> Acts Chap. 26.18.15.32.
<hi>The remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſins, and regeneration of ſinners,</hi> Acts 26. Chapter 18. ver. and 1 Corin. Chap. 4. verſ. 15. <hi>The new birth of ſouls, and to believe in himſelf,</hi> James Chap. 1. verſe 18. and 1 Corinth. Chap. 3 verſ. 5. <hi>The ſubduing of ſin and Satan, and the ſalvation of Saints,</hi> 2 Corinth. Chap. 10. verſe 4.5. and 1 Corinth. Chap. 1. verſe 21. And 3. If <hi>our Lord Chriſt doth not now extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily ſend forth any,</hi> as it's plain hee doth not: neither
<hi>immediately deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out any perſons, nor delivering to any a power of miracles.</hi> I ſay, if ſo; then of neceſſity, the ordinary way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting this Office, and of ſending out ſuch Officers, which was given in charge to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> are of a continuing obligation, and of conſant obſervation in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Jeſus Chriſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. Let me put you in mind but of one thing more, and this is, <hi>the Elegant titles</hi> that are given to Miniſters, which do all beſpeak a neceſſity, not onely of <pb n="39" facs="tcp:171453:38"/>being qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ified for this Office, but of having the Office committed to them. Are not Miniſters c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lled the <hi>Angels</hi> of the Churches, <hi>Revelations Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſe</hi> 20. the
<hi>overſeers</hi> of the Church? <hi>Acts Chap.</hi> 20. <hi>ver.</hi> 28. the <hi>rulers</hi> of the Church? <hi>Hebrews Chap.</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 7. Yea, and <hi>ſuch rulers they are in, and ſo over the Church, as are to be counted worthy of double honour,</hi> 1 <hi>Timothy Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi>
17. and 1 <hi>Theſ. Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 12.13. Are they not the
<hi>Stewards</hi> of Chriſt? 1 <hi>Corinht</hi> 4.1. The <hi>Heralds</hi> of Chriſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? <hi>Romans</hi> 10. <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. Yea, and the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſadours</hi> of Chriſt, 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 20. Are they not termed <hi>watchmen? Heb.</hi>
13.17. <hi>builders?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10. and <hi>ſouldiers?</hi> 2
<hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now what leſſe do any of theſe apart, or can all theſe together intimate? than that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ſhould be furniſhed with authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as well as fitted with ability? and muſt bee able to ſhew a commiſſion, as well as ſpeak of qualifications? In a word, <hi>that they muſt have a deligation from our Saviour to this employment, as wel as a diſpoſition in their ſpirits to this employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:171453:39"/>
            <p>Sect. 4. Fourthly, how is this Office of being Teachers in the Church to bee committed unto ſuch, as are duly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified? You will eaſily obſerve, that we are not enquiring about committing the Office to
<hi>extraordinary teachers;</hi> ſuch as are <hi>by immediate deligation</hi> from Chriſt immediate I mean, not only <hi>ratione vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis, ſed ſuppoſiti in regard of power, but of perſon.</hi> This caſe falls not within our compaſſe; when ſuch <hi>immediate furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (as were herewith given) for the Miniſtry, and therefore ſuch immediate ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitures with the Miniſtery, have no place.</hi> But our enquiry is about the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this office to <hi>Ordinary teachers, by mediate deligation</hi> from Chriſt <hi>i. e.</hi> by his Officers, who in his name, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Ordinance, are to ſeparate them to this ſervice of his, in his Church.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hujus, Miniſterij jus per ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municare ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>â ratione vocatio ordinarii Miniſtri eſt media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta. Hoc au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſic eſt intellgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, ut authoritas adminiſtrandi res divinas à Deo immediatè communicetur miniſtris omnibus legitimis, &amp; deſignatio perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum in quas confertur fiat per Eccleſiam.</hi> Ameſ. Medul. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol. l. 1. c. 35. n. 5. &amp; 6.</note> And thus briefly, this Office is to bee committed to men duly qualified, 1 by the Presbytery. 2 after proof. 3 with prayer and faſting. 4. and with putting on of their hands.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:171453:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Sect. 1. <hi>By the Prebytery</hi> i. e. by presbyters in Office; whoſe part it was in the Ordination of <hi>Timothy.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi>
4.14. Their common care and charge it was, and not <hi>Pauls</hi> only. 2
<hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. <hi>We never read Paul to have practiced in, or to have pretended to a ſole power of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination; or to ſo much as a negative voice in that particular,</hi> though (no doubt) he had a greater latitude of authority, than any can now lay claim to, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an <hi>Apoſtle, not of, or by man, but by Jeſus Chriſt: Yet Paul was neither ordained nor did Ordain, without the concurrence of ſome other Act.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3.
<hi>ch.</hi> 14.23.
<q rend="margQuotes">'If any will yet implead ordination by a
<hi>presbytery,</hi> becauſe without a <hi>Prelate;</hi> 1 <hi>he ought to produce the divine inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Prelate diſtinct from a dignified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond a Presbyter or Miniſter.</hi> Certain we are, <hi>the Apoſtles have left no ſuch one, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their liſt of Church Officers; Eph.</hi> 4 11.
<hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6, 7, 8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. and clear it is, that a
<hi>Biſhop and Presbyter are all one in the language of the Scripture,</hi>
               </q>
               <note n="a)" place="margin">See <hi>ſect.</hi> 2.</note>
               <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.10.
<note n="b)" place="margin">vid. Hieronym. ad Loc. <hi>Idem eſt ergo Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter, qui Epiſcopus &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 2.
<note n="c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Poſt Epiſcopum Diaconi ordinationem ſubjicit. Quare? iſt quia Epiſcopi &amp; Presbyteri una ordinatio eſt? uter<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> exim ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eerdos eſt.</hi> Ambroſ. ad Loc.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> having <pb n="42" facs="tcp:171453:40"/>the ſame office, the ſame ordination, the ſame characters given to, and qualitier
<q rend="margQuotes">'required in them, and the ſame work being committed to them. And as clear 'tis that <hi>a Presbyter or ordinary Miniſter is veſted with a power of government or rule.</hi>
               </q> 1
<hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7, 17. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12.
<hi>Act.</hi> 20.17, 28. 2. <hi>Hee ought to prove the divine inveſtiture of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates with Ordination ard impoſition of hands different from presbyters,</hi> whereof
<q rend="margQuotes">'we read not <hi>one word in all the Scriptures,</hi> but of the <hi>laying on of the hands of the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery</hi> in fair and open characters,</q> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. True
'tis that we read of Ordination by <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, by <hi>Paul</hi> and
<hi>Barnabas</hi> Apoſtles, but this neither <hi>directly</hi> ſerveth the cauſe of the Prelates, they being nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtles nor Evangeliſts, nor
<hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly,</hi> unleſſe they can prove them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be a diſtinct order or dignity of Miniſters, by the divine appointment of Jeſus Chriſt, &amp; in that ſence can put in a plea of being their
<hi>ſucceſſors which a Presbyter in a fair conſtruction may,</hi>
               </q> 1
<hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1, 2. <hi>Though a Prelate without a forced conſtruction cannot.</hi> Where doth <pb n="43" facs="tcp:171453:40"/>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'the Scripture preſcribe that there ſhould be any ordination <hi>of Prelates</hi> different from, or over and above their former ordination as <hi>Preſbyters?</hi> Or that there ſhould be any Ordination by <hi>prelates</hi> as diſtinct from Presbyters? When it is a ruled caſe, that a Biſhop or Prelate or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained <hi>per ſaltum</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> who never had the Ordination of a Presbyter himſelf, but only of a Biſhop) can neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate and adminiſter the Sacrament of the Lords body, nor ordain a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter:</q>
               <note n="d)" place="margin">of the Church. <hi>l.</hi> 3.
<hi>ch.</hi> 39.</note> by which it appeareth, that a <hi>Biſhop doth not excell a Presbyter by a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and higher order or power of order;</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'for which Doctor <hi>Field</hi> hath produced the acknowledgment of the moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned among the Papiſts.
<note n="d)" place="margin">Aquin. Bonavent. Dominic, à Soto. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macanus. Camerar. &amp; Contare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> 
                  <hi>(e)</hi> The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> as if Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of
<hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Crete,</hi> will be a covering too narrow. For as we never read the Spirit of God calling them Biſhops in Scripture, (the Poſt-ſcript to thoſe Epiſtles being diſowned from being any part of the Canon by many Papiſts, even by <hi>Baronius</hi> and the
<hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts;</hi> and are ſo <hi>diſproved</hi> by ſeverall Proteſtants,</q>
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>vide Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za Anot. maj. ad</hi> 1 Tim.
6.22. <hi>ad</hi> 2 Tim. 4.23. <hi>ad</hi> Tit. 3.14.</note> So, <hi>Timothy is expreſly <pb n="44" facs="tcp:171453:41"/>enough called an Evangeliſt.</hi> 2
<hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5.
<q rend="margQuotes">'Nor could their frequent removes,
<note n="g" place="margin">ſee them deſcribed <hi>Jus Divin. Min. Evan. par.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 69. <hi>Smectimnu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſect.</hi> 13.</note> after the mention of their being at <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus</hi> and
<hi>Crete,</hi>
               </q> have any conſiſtence
<q rend="margQuotes">'with the charge or Office of a Biſhop, which obligeth to a fixed reſidence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his flock?</q> (to paſſe other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<note n="h" place="margin">ſee <hi>Jus Di vin. Miniſt. Evang. par.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5. throughout</note> againſt their dioceſan
<hi>Epiſcopacy</hi>)
<q rend="margQuotes">'Their <hi>frequent diverſions</hi> and journeys, and <hi>various diſpatches</hi> to and fro, at the
<hi>deſire</hi> of the Apoſtles, and as might beſt ſubſerve the
<hi>deſign</hi> and welfare of the <hi>generall</hi> viſible Church, do loudly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough proclaim them to be <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> I know there are on the other hand that veſt the people with this power and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of Ordination,</q> beyond what was ever poſſeſſed by the
<hi>Prelates.</hi> But with no <hi>countenance</hi> that I know from Chriſt, yea, or conveniency to Chriſtians; while it is little other than a ſeed-plot of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions among them, and of diviſions into parties; and while beſide their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the power of ruling, whoſe place it is to be ruled; ſuch are their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abilities &amp; diſproportion to make proof of mens ready inſtruction to the kingdom of God, either in cleering the difficulties of the Goſpel, or in e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cing gainſayers. <pb n="45" facs="tcp:171453:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>'Tis true; We read (whatſome ingeniouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerve before us
<note n="k)" place="margin">London Miniſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in their <hi>Jns div. min. evan.</hi> par. 3. c. 13.</note> of Ordaining El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <hi>in every Church,</hi> but we never read of Ordaining Elders <hi>by any Church. They Ordained them Elders in every Church, Act.</hi> 14.23. Who Ordained them? <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> for the people, not the people for themſelves. That every Church ſhould Ordain them Elders in every Church, grates too much upon common ſenſe and truth. Nor will the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> help it out, for what ever bee the import of
<note n="l)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>i.e.</hi> To ſtretch out the hand; which is ſtill done in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, with impoſition of hands. Nor can there much more be evinced by the uſage of this word in this place, if there be any worth in that obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of learned
<hi>Stepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> that it ſignifieth not to give ſuffrage, but to create, ordain, &amp;c. when it governs an accuſarive caſe, as here it doth. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Steph. Theſaur Ling.</hi> graec. ad verbum
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> manifeſt enough it is, both from what is antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to this expreſſion, and what is after it, that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> were the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to whom <hi>[they]</hi> muſt neceſſarily bee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to relate nine times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, in the narrative or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation which is herewith made, <hi>ver.</hi> 21. <hi>ad finem.</hi> Far be it from mee, to diveſt the Churches of Jeſus from any part of thoſe priviledges, which are given them by <pb n="46" facs="tcp:171453:42"/>his charter? Let it be granted them for me, that the <hi>people may chooſe;</hi> and look out men, and ſet them before the Presbytery, as they did for Deacons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtles, ſtill obſerving their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.3,
5, 6. But the <hi>Presbytery 'tis, that commit the Miniſtry,</hi> appoint and ſend forth the men, as then did the Apoſtles, <hi>ver.</hi> 3.6. Peruſe I beſeech you the primitive practiſe, the records of all thoſe Ordinations, which you finde in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, 1.6.13.14.
<hi>Chapt.</hi> &amp; what prints read you, or the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcureſt trace of the peoples putting men into the Office of Miniſters? Peruſe to theſe, the Epiſtles that moſt particularly treat of, and purpoſely take up this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject or argument, thoſe to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus:</hi> and yet tell us where may wee finde the <hi>ſmalleſt</hi> track or footſtep?
'Las! if the peoples ſuffrage had been enough to ſet men in Office, what need ſuch <hi>preſſing arguments</hi> from <hi>Paul</hi> to
<hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus?</hi> and ſuch <hi>particular inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of them with this buſineſs, that they Ordain Elders in
<hi>Crete</hi> and <hi>Epheſus?</hi> Doth he write at this rate, in any one of all the Epiſtles he ſendeth to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches? <pb n="47" facs="tcp:171453:42"/>or in either of theſe Epiſtles ſent to theſe Officers, that the Churches ſee to the Ordaining of Elders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Again, if ſo; what need or right had <hi>Paul</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſs himſelf or <hi>Barnabas</hi> ſo far, as to Ordain Elders in every Church, at <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra, Icontum,</hi> and
<hi>Antioch, &amp;c. Act.</hi> 14.19.23 Would they have ſo abuſed their own power, or the peoples priviledges, as by this to have been arraigned for bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie-bodies in other mens matters? which they might have been, had Ordination been in the power and right of the Churches. 'Tis true, we may be proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough called the Miniſters and Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of the Churches, ſo far as I know. But how? Not as if they were the <hi>originall,</hi> but are the <hi>object</hi> of our authoritative miſſion and meſſages; not as if we were <hi>ſent from, and by them</hi> into this Office, but as
<hi>ſent to and for them</hi> for their obedience and joy of faith: unleſs men may be ſaid to ſend meſſengers to themſelves,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 2 The Miniſtry is not to bee committed till after probation or triall made. Oh that dreadfull charge! <hi>I charge thee before God and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <pb n="48" facs="tcp:171453:43"/>and the Elect Angels—lay hands ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on no man,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21.22.
<hi>Timothy</hi> muſt not, for ſo much as the Office of a Deacon, therefore ſurely not for the Office of a Biſhop or Miniſter. Let theſe <hi>alſo firſt</hi> bee proved; then let them uſe the Office of a Deacon, 1
<hi>Tim.</hi> 3.10. 'Tis an abuſe then to put men into the Office of the Miniſtry, before or without proof made. Nor may this proof bee ſlight and overly, but muſt bee <hi>diligent</hi> and <hi>diſtinctive.</hi>
               <note n="n)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>est prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>è explorare qualis in ſe res ſit, &amp; a diverſis aut contrariis diſcernere inquit Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reus. Nec ſolummodo probare, ſed approbare ſigniſicat, ut po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> perſpectum, ſic apud</hi> Luc. 14.19. &amp; 1 Pet. 1.7. &amp; Phil. 1.10. &amp; 1 Theſ. 2.4 &amp;
<hi>apud Plutarc. de</hi> Inſtit. liber. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Proved they ſhould bee, in their ſpirituall and inward call to the Miniſtry, and in their ſuitable qualifications for the Miniſtry. What they are for
<hi>life?</hi> what for <hi>learning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and what they are like to be for <hi>labour?</hi> What are their <hi>purpoſes</hi> by it? what i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their <hi>proportion</hi> to it? and what will bee their <hi>perſeverance</hi> in it? In a word; what of God and grace is to be found in them? and what of forwardneſs and zeal there is and will be for God?</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:171453:43"/>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>With prayer and faſting.</hi> Such was the primitive practiſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.6. &amp; 13.3. &amp; 14.23. and ſtands upon record as our pattern. Whether theſe enter the eſſence of Ordination, I ſay not: but ſure I am, that they are of eminent and excellent obſervation and uſe. Is our Lord himſelf therefore about to chooſe, and authoritatively to ſend abroad Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles? <hi>He continueth all night before it in prayer to God, and when it was day he called unto him his Diſciples, and of them hee choſe Twelve whom alſo he named Apoſtles, Luk.</hi> 6.12, 13. Ah ſirs! <hi>pray, pray,</hi> you that want and would have Paſtors. <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting prayers, will make fervent preachers.</hi> We beſeech you brethren, for the Lord Jeſus Chriſt's ſake, and for the love of the Spirit, that yee will ſtrive together with us in your prayers to God,
<note n="o)" place="margin">Rom. 15.30.</note> this day. <hi>Oh the weakneſſes of our perſons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the work we are to perform! the worth and weight of God's preſence! and our want of your prayers, which if earneſt, will be ſure to be effectuall prayers</hi>
               <note n="p)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 5.16.</note>! Pray ye there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the Lord of the Harveſt, that he wil ſend forth theſe expectants, Labourers into his Harveſt
<note n="q)" place="margin">Mat. 9.38.</note>.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:171453:44"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. With impoſition of hands. Thus <hi>Timothy was Ordained,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>and was to Ordain,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim</hi>
5.22. What though Papiſts have <hi>placed it among the Sacraments?</hi> muſt wee therefore <hi>pluck it from among the Saints?</hi> although <hi>Paul preſerveth it among the principles of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, Heb.</hi> 6
1, 2. (under what notion, or to what purpoſe, I ſhall not diſpute) Surely
<hi>their dotage</hi> on it, will be a poor Apologie for <hi>our deniall</hi> or <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing</hi> of it, upon whom the true light hath ſhined: eſpecially when <hi>the whole ſolemnity of Ordination is once and again ſet forth by this one Ceremony;</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. and 5.22. 2
<hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. and you hear none of us pleading for it as a
<hi>Sacrament;</hi> though we would not be put by from any <hi>ſolemn right;</hi> eſpecially if an <hi>inſeparable adjunct</hi> to an Ordinance of Chriſt. Is <hi>Timothy</hi> enjoyned to lay hands ſuddenly on no man? 1
<hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. what leſs can be implyed, than that he lay hands ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly upon ſome, at leaſt after mature ſcrutiny? I ſhall not expatiate, but if (beſide the concurrent profeſſion and practice of the reformed Churches
<note n="r)" place="margin">See a brief view of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence herein of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered you by Dr. <hi>Seaman</hi> in his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, at the beginning Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ion 3.</note> if <pb n="51" facs="tcp:171453:44"/>
               <hi>Paul,</hi> ſo pretious a Saint, and ſo profound a Scholar, did thus <hi>accept</hi> it in his own Ordination to the Miniſtry, as hee did,
<hi>Act.</hi> 13.3. and did thus <hi>act and aſſiſt</hi> in the Ordination of others, as hee did, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. God forbid! that I, or any other ſhould ſo much liſten to pride, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, or what ever elſe it bee, as to <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitate it cauſleſly!</hi> or to <hi>harden my ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it contem trouſly.</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>Paul</hi>'s preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption and precedent me thinks will be enough to acquit and anſwer for us, though we had nothing elſe to render in account, why we retain this ancient rite: by which, yet <hi>publick offices</hi> have been wont to be conveighed, <hi>Numb.</hi>
27.18, 23. and 8.10. <hi>Act.</hi> 6.6. and <hi>this partacularly,</hi> 1
<hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. 'Tis true, when <hi>Paul</hi> enjoins <hi>Titus</hi> to Ordain El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in every City, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.5. hee doth not preſcribe expreſly, impoſition of hands. Nor doth he <hi>prohibit</hi> it; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>points it out, not obſcurely,</hi> by two things (though the common practice thereof in thoſe times might have been intimation enough to him, and a juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication for it, againſt this exception.) 1. By leading him back to former in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions <pb n="52" facs="tcp:171453:45"/>[as I had appointed thee] wherein if wee may make judgment, from what <hi>Paul</hi> practiſed,
<note n="ſ)" place="margin">Act. 14.23 2 Tim. 1.6.</note> to what
<hi>Paul preſcribed,</hi> this could not but make one particular, eſpecially, if the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive included in that precept to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> 1 <hi>Chap.</hi>
5.22. bee put with it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame ſcale. 2. By the light of the Word
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (rendered here by ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in and in <hi>Acts</hi> 6.3. by appoint) which the Apoſtles practice had alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy interpreted, to import the laying on of hands, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.6. as one particular requiſite to that publick and ſolemn work. I know it is pretended that the Holy Ghoſt was miraculouſly given by impoſition of hands in Ordination, and thence it is pleaded, that the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle now ceaſing, ſo doth the myſtery too. But how is the former
<hi>proved and juſtified?</hi> And if; yet how the latter is therefrom
<hi>pleaded or inferred</hi> I ſee not; unleſs we ſhall upon the ſame ground now relinquiſh prayer, becauſe it's no more effectuall to heal the ſick, or rai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the dead, as it was formerly. <hi>Act.</hi> 9.37, 40, 41. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.14, 15. We hear the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles <hi>requiring</hi> them to look out ſeven <pb n="53" facs="tcp:171453:45"/>men <hi>full of the Holy Ghoſt, that they may</hi> lay hands upon them, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.3. <hi>cum</hi> 6. but never hear them <hi>relating</hi> ſo much as one that had <hi>received the Holy Ghoſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had layd their hands upon him, in his Ordination.</hi> I ſay in his
<hi>Ordination:</hi> for it is granted that the Holy Ghoſt was given, by the laying on of hands, in the other caſes, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.17.18. and 19.6. Why muſt <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> (think we) receive ſatisfaction touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mens gifts before Ordination? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. and <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. And why muſt they till then retard and ſtave off their Ordination, 1
<hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. If laying on of hands would have conferred that ſpirit upon men, from whom all gifts come? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.8. <hi>ad</hi> 12. True it is, we read of <hi>Timothie's</hi> gift by the laying on of <hi>Paul's</hi> hands, and of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. But not of the Holy Ghoſts being given him hereby. It is rather <hi>the gift of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry</hi> that is intended in theſe Scriptures, than <hi>gifts for the Miniſtry,</hi> and perhaps, may bee therefore mentioned in both places not plurally, but ſingularly <hi>[the gift.]</hi> That offices are called
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:171453:46"/>gifts, and particularly the Miniſtry, compare
<hi>Ep.</hi> 4 8, 11. between which the 9 and 10 verles, fall as within a Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis: the 11 verſ. giving us th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in particulars of what had been expreſſed at the 8 ver. ingeneral:
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſti duo verſus</hi> (<hi>ſc.</hi> 9.10) <hi>per parea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſin l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>guntur, nam mox ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſu</hi> 11.
<hi>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dit ad ſupe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iora, hoc eſt, ad explicanda dona ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> de qu b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s dixerat in genere, dedit dona hominibus Zanch. ad Epheſ.</hi>
4.10</note> And ſo is an appofite anſwer to every one that asks this queſtion; what are thoſe gifts, when Chriſt aſcended up on high, which he received for
<note n="(t)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.18.</note> and give unto men? He gave ſom Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and ſom Prophets, and ſom Evang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, and ſom Paſtors and Teachers.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>5</label> Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thly one thing is yet behind. Why muſt thoſe that are authoritatively from Chriſt to teach others in the Church, have the Office committed to them, as well as be qualified for that office? Why? It is for the honour of Chriſt, for the happineſſe of the Church, and for the hope and heartning of ſuch teachers themſelves.</p>
            <p>Sect. 1. <hi>It is for the honour of Chriſt.</hi> Which is the great deſign, that grace hath to carry on, by all the various me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:171453:46"/>and miniſtrations of it, by all Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, and by all Ordinances. Had he thrown the reyns of his Church, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and cauſe looſe, to the <hi>liberty,</hi> or rather <hi>luſts</hi> of men, <hi>take hee that will: teach he that will:</hi> who could have then read ſuch his
<hi>accurate prudence?</hi> ſuch his <hi>abſolute power?</hi> and ſuch his <hi>affluence of perfections,</hi> as are now made legible in treating his own affairs; by thoſe only that are of his own appointment, and can ſhew his royall patent? Alas! what conveniency would this at all bear to his tranſcendant dignity, and moſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king glory, whereof the greateſt royalties are but poor reſemblances? Wil men call him the <hi>wonderfull Counſellor, the Prince of peace,
<note n="u)" place="margin">Iſ. 9.6.7</note> the King of kings, and Lord of Lords?</hi>
               <note n="*)" place="margin">Rev. 19.16.</note> that either hath never a Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, Herald, Embaſſadour, or ſo much as a Steward by office, by whom the grand importances of his Court and Crown may be tranſacted on the one hand? or is ſo little tender of theſe great truſts, and his own tranſactions on the other; that whoſoever hath but will and skill, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head and fitneſs enough, may without further leave from him or his, lay hold <pb n="56" facs="tcp:171453:47"/>upon theſe offices, and leap into the higheſt honour? Need I remind you, that ſuch are the offices, ſuch is the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be a Miniſter of Jeſus? Is it ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually? Well; the more ſpirituall the office and honour is, the more need in a juſt ſenſe, of his putting them into a ſecurity, from the fleſhly preſumptions and forward pretenſions of vain men, who are but too deſirous of being teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of others, even before they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what they ſay, or whereof they affirm themſelves, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7. or at leaſt of heaping unto themſelves teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, having itching ears, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3. It is true, I acknowledge, that pious Miniſters are ſo far from being accounted ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to the honour of Chriſt; that wee are made rather with
<hi>Paul,</hi> the filth of the world, and the off-ſcouring of all things, 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. But what ſaith <hi>Paul? God, who commanded the light to ſhine out of darkneſs, hath ſhined in our hearts, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. and if our brethren be enquired of (ſaith he) <hi>they are the glory of Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. <hi>ver.</hi> 23. And no marvail, for beſides the <pb n="57" facs="tcp:171453:47"/>
               <hi>expreſſions</hi> to his glory by them, ſuch are the <hi>ampreſſions</hi> of his glory upon them, not onely in their Miniſteriall <hi>gifts and graces,</hi> which beſpeak them qualified for this Office by Chriſt, but in the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall
<hi>authority and adminiſtrations,</hi> which beſpeak them Commiſſioned to this Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice from Chriſt. And indeed, what other are his Miniſters, Paſtors, and Teachers among us; but the <hi>ſpeaking gifts, and ſtanding pledges of Chriſt's glorious aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for us? and of his gracious and great affections to us, Epheſ.</hi> 4.8, 11. compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. <hi>It is for the happineſs of the Church</hi> likewiſe, which is next to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers honour, in the aym and heart of Chriſt. It is for her <hi>enlargement, edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and eſtabliſhment,</hi> as the Apoſtle at large inſtanceth and illuſtrateth in the ſame, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.12, 13, 14, 15.
<hi>verſes.</hi> For the perfecting of the Saints, &amp;c. Throw open but this door once, that gifts, and a deſire to exerciſe them make a Miniſter, and you may (too late) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive well-nigh, <hi>all that is dear</hi> to the Church <hi>going out, and whatſoever is divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and deſtructive coming in,</hi> by the ſame <pb n="58" facs="tcp:171453:48"/>door, both ſpeedily and irremediably. What <hi>Corah</hi> and his complices will not tell <hi>Aaron and Moſes too? Ye take too much upon you; ſeeing all the Congregation are holy, every one of them, and the Lord is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them: wherefore then lift you up your ſelves above the Congregation of the Lord, Numb.</hi> 163 Nor could I ever yet hear of any thing more eminent among them, than is error and confuſion, who have taken qualifications to give Commiſſion. Alas! this muſt needs break the unity, and blaſt the purity of the Churches quickly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>N,</hi> 1. <hi>It muſt needs break the unity of the Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ches,</hi> (a bleſſing how deſirable in it ſelf? and how dear to our Saviour) if nothing but
<hi>fitneſs</hi> and <hi>forwardneſs</hi> bee requiſite to make an Officer or Miniſter. Wo to the Common-wealth of this Iſrael! If every one that had ability, had therefore authority too; If every one that probably is, or preſumeth himſelf to be fit for ſuch or ſuch an Office, were thereby put into it, and muſt be ſo obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; or if every one, who is qualified for, muſt bee therefore counted a Judge, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, yea, or but a Conſtable.
<hi>Hath God <pb n="59" facs="tcp:171453:48"/>provided against ſuch intruſions upon civill Offices? and will he permit it in ſacred? Taken ſuch care in order to the accord and quiet of the Common wealth? and hath he thrown it by with reſpect to his Church, which is ſo much dearer to him than are all the Societies in the world beſide?</hi> Who would be <hi>ruled,</hi> if but to preſume our ſelvs qualified, would make us <hi>rulers,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Church or State? Surely this would make the <hi>militant Church,</hi> like that
<hi>military body,</hi> where qualifications to command were a commiſſion for a Company: <hi>The Church ſhould have all Officers and no Souldiers quickly;</hi> and if it did not run with ſuch an army into <hi>blood</hi> and
<hi>confuſion,</hi> yet would <hi>ſoon</hi> and <hi>ſurely</hi> run with it into <hi>bitterneſſe</hi> and <hi>contentions.</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'He that can ſecure me the peace and unity of that Kingdome, where every one that is fit, may be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<hi>ſupreme;</hi> or of that County, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> every one that is fit, may be thereby
<hi>Sheriffe;</hi> or but of that <hi>Corporation,</hi> where every one that is fit, may be thereby <hi>Major,</hi> ſhall be (with me) <hi>a none-ſuch</hi> among men, and may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, if any, that the beauty and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:171453:49"/>of the Churches of Jeſus may be preſerved too, wherein every one that judgeth himſelf fit, is thereby made a Miniſter and Officer. Let me add <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his, <hi>if Miniſters are not Officers,* the Church hath none:</hi> For who elſe can ſhew me ſo clear evidences? And if men may bee bold with this Office in the Church, to inveſt themſelves with it, and to execute at pleaſure, why they ſhould be back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to, or baulk any other Office, I know not:</q> For
<hi>this of all others is moſt ſacred and moſt circumſcribed. And if all Offices lye in common where ſhall we look for the Churches Concord?</hi> Ah Sirs! have wee read the 12 to the <hi>Romans</hi> from the the 3 to the 9, or the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12? And can we think our bleſſed head and Maſter, in whom are hid all the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of wiſdome and kindneſſe, ſo remiſſe about conferring Offices? and ſo regardleſſe of the Churches concord as this amounts to? What! are there ſo many unities? and all with reſpect had to the Church? <hi>One body, and one ſpirit, even as they are called in one hope of their calling; one Lord, one faith, one baptiſm, one God and <pb n="61" facs="tcp:171453:49"/>Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in them all? Eph.</hi> 4.5, 6. <hi>Lo, therefore Chriſt hath given Paſtours and Teachers</hi> (names of Office) <hi>verſe</hi> 8, 11. <hi>that they may keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</hi> verſe 3.
<hi>and that till we all come in the unity of the faith &amp;c. ver.</hi>
13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>N.</hi> 2. <hi>This will blast the purity of the Churches</hi> too, and let in (what not?) that is deſtructive to <hi>verity, and the power of Godlineſſe.</hi> If our ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring times have not given ſufficient teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie to this ſad truth, I know not what times ever did or ſhall. <hi>What through uncalled Preachers, and uncate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed hearers, Oh! the havock and convulſions that are made in the Churches of Jeſus!</hi> And ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, who can expect; but <hi>that thoſe, who will vainly or violently enter upon the Miniſtery without Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſhall likewiſe venturouſly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy themſelves in it, without obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation? Witneſſe thoſe falſe teachers whereof</hi> Peter
<hi>tells vs.</hi> 2 Peter, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 2. and Jude, from the fourth to the twentieth verſe. Who may, or <hi>how can wee expect <pb n="62" facs="tcp:171453:50"/>other, than unſetledneſſe in the love of the Goſpell? and unſoundneſſe in the life of godlineſſe from that man, or men, who ſhake off the order of the Goſpell? Surely, they that heap to themſelvs teachers, walk but after their own luſts therein, and have it ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ears, turned from the truth, and unto fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3, 4. And therefore whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they that make themſelvs teachers are like to walk in the law of God, and to lead you in the ways of that truth which is according to godlineſſe, judg ye? What leſſe can be ſaid than this? That
<hi>meaſuring themſelvs by themſelves, and comparing themſelvs among themſelvs, they are not wiſe:</hi> and if the premiſſes be conſidered, <hi>how wicked!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sect. 3. <hi>It's for the beartning and comfort of ſuch teachers,</hi> that beſide qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications, they ſhall have the Office committed to them: their comfortable incouragement much conducing to the credit and intereſſe of that King Jeſus, whoſe Embaſſadours they are. Sirs! <hi>the duties, difficulties, and diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Miniſters, how various are they? how involved!</hi> And alas! what ſorry things are our beſt qualifications <pb n="63" facs="tcp:171453:50"/>to ſupport us, without the ſtrong aid of that grace, which ſets before us the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of our Commiſſion, to ſtay and cheer our hearts. Who of us, my brethren, but muſt confeſs with <hi>Paul,</hi> that <hi>wee are not ſufficient of our ſelvs, ſo much as to think any thing as of our ſelvs?</hi> Where then is our
<hi>ſufficiencie?</hi> and what is our <hi>ſupport?</hi> Our sufficiency is of God, who alſo hath made us able Miniſters of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 2
<hi>Cor,</hi> 3.5, 6. <hi>That God, who hath made us Ministors, is the ſpring head of our ſufficiencies in the diſcharge and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of our Ministry; and that God hath made us Miniſters, is the ſtay and baſis of our hopes in all the difficult emergencies of our Miniſtry.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">See 2 Tim. 1.11, 12.</note> That our God hath ſent us, is the ſtabliſhing conſideration, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all deſpondencies and diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that he will ſupply, ſtrengthen, ſecure, and work all our works in us and for us. And Lo, by this it is, that God would have us to <hi>chide down our fears, and to keep up our faith. I ſanctified thee, ſaith he to</hi> Jeremie, <hi>and I ordained thee a Prophet unto the Nations.</hi> Doth <hi>Jeremie</hi> ſay? A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord God! I am a child, behold I cannot ſpeak. Ay, but hear what the <pb n="64" facs="tcp:171453:51"/>Lord ſaith unto
<hi>Jeremy:</hi> ſay not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> am a child, for thou ſhalt go to all that I ſhall ſend thee, and whatſoever I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand thee thou ſhalt ſpeak: <hi>Be not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of their faces; for I am with thee to deliver thee ſaith the Lord; Behold, I have made thee a defenced City,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7, 8, 18, 19. An beloved, God doth therefore Commiſſion us, to corroborate and comfort our hearts, and to confirm us you ſee againſt hardſhips.
<q rend="margQuotes">'Oh the tears and tentations, that every man of God is ſubject to! without are fightings, within are fears: And in the midd'ſt of ſo many <hi>inward diſtractions, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſtreſſes;</hi> while ſuch is the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of our province, ſuch the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity of our perſons, ſuch the deceitfulneſs of ſin, ſuch the deiuſions of Satan, ſuch the deſperate ſtubborneſs of the world, ſuch the depths and heights of the Word, and ſuch the danger and worth of immortall ſouls, for which we muſt give an account; In the midd'ſt of all this, how would our <hi>hearts gather aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment!</hi> and our <hi>hopes go down into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair,</hi> did not the ſenſe of this truth, and the ſweet fruits that grow upon it ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:171453:51"/>our ſouls: If God hath <hi>ſent.</hi> God will
<hi>ſecond</hi> me; if God hath <hi>put me into</hi> the Miniſtry, he will
<hi>proſper me</hi> in the Miniſtry; if he hath <hi>given me a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> he will not <hi>deny me his conour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence;</hi> he that
<hi>appointed me</hi> to this Office, will accompliſh his ends by and upon me in this Office: <hi>Theſe, theſe are the comforts of a Commiſſioned, if conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Miniſter.</hi> Be the ſucceſs what it wil, if he be ſincere and ſent, he is to God a ſweet ſavour, though in them that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15, 16. and God is his ſtrength and reward; though he hath ſpent his own ſtrength to no purpoſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi>
49.4, 5.</q>
            </p>
            <p>A ſtranger, an unofficed preacher hath not to intermeddle with this joy. But Oh the ſweet Cordiall! and com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſavour, of our inveſtitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e with the Office both unto us and you! when both you and we ſhall call to mind; that we are not barely the
<hi>ſervants,</hi> but the <hi>ſtewards</hi> of Chriſt; or onely the
<hi>ſubjects,</hi> but the <hi>Embaſſadours of Chriſt,</hi> and ſo whatſoever we bind or looſe, beſeech or charge, rebuke or comfort,
<hi>it's as if God did it; as though God did beſeech you <pb n="66" facs="tcp:171453:52"/>by us; we pray you in Chriſt's ſtead,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. Chriſt hath bid us go teach, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Lo, I am with you,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. But the unofficed preacher hath neither part nor lot in this promiſe; for be it ſuppoſed, that Chriſt hath given him feet, beſtowed abilities; yet hath he not bid him go, granted him authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and
<hi>who can hope, that Chriſt will go with him, that goeth before Chriſt, or rather ſteals away before he ſent him?</hi> Will hee be with the Prophets that run, and he not ſent them? Nay, <hi>I am againſt theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, ſaith the Lord, Jeremi.</hi> 23.21.30.31, 32.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE.</head>
               <p>Having thus explained and evinced the <hi>aſſertion</hi> or obſervation; give mee leave now to exerciſe my ſelf and you, a while, in the <hi>application.</hi> I ſhall not be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry long; neither the ſtraights of time,
<note n="*" place="margin">There being 13. afterward to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained.</note> nor indeed my ſtrength, permitting it. I ſhal therefore lay but three Uſes of this point before you. The firſt for humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and conſternation, the ſecond for holy caution, the third in way of hearty counſell.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:171453:52"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. <hi>Of humbling conſternation.</hi> Is it ſo, that ſuch as are to teach authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively in the Church, or Miniſters of Chriſt, muſt be both men qualified for the Office, and have the Office commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them? Oh! what matter of hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling conſternation and holy confuſion before the Lord doth this call for from us this day? Oh that mine head were waters, &amp; mine eyes a fountain of tears, that I might weep day and night for the ſlain (ſhall I ſay, or for the ſouls?) of the daughter of my people, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.1. Partly through unqualified Miniſters of the one ſide, and partly through uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned Miniſters on the other ſide. Oh the ravine and ruine, that is made of multitudes of ſouls! one whereof is more worth than all <hi>England,</hi> all the <hi>Indies,</hi> yea, than all the world. Ah firs! how have holy things been profaned? how have heavenly things been pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? and how much, how long have wholeſome truths been perverted, what between this and that extream? Who of us is ſuch a ſtranger in <hi>England</hi> but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>deafe</hi> doth <hi>hear?</hi> that unleſs <hi>blind</hi> doth <hi>ſee?</hi> and unleſs <hi>ſenſuall or ſtupid,</hi> 
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:171453:53"/>but muſt
<hi>ſigh,</hi> and <hi>ſmite upon our thighs,</hi> in the ſad remembrances of there things! Oh! how hath God been and is yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured by it? How hath the Goſpel bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and is yet deſpiſed by it? and how hath godlineſs be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, and is yet derided for it, to this day? Ay, and for this, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all our engagements and endeavours for a Reformation, the land mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and lyeth unreformed, even to this hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And now, Oh that we could (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure I am that we ſhould) mourn be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord for theſe things.</p>
               <p>Sect. 1. <hi>Let us mourn for unqualified Miniſters.</hi> O believed! how many have walked (and Oh that I ſhould mention it without weeping!) <hi>walked under the calling of Miniſter, that have not been wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be caded men?</hi> but have been ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like the Mule for ignorance the, Goat for luſt and the Swine for drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſſe, than like the Miniſters of Jeſus; ſuch whoſe <hi>God</hi> hath been their
<hi>belly,</hi> whoſe <hi>Goſpel</hi> hath been their <hi>barn,</hi> whoſe <hi>glory</hi> hath been their <hi>ſhame. Non Paſtores, ſed praedatores; non prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cones, ſed praedones,</hi> as <hi>Bernard</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ad Cleru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sermo in Cencilio
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hemenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly declaimeth the prophane Prieſts, <pb n="69" facs="tcp:171453:53"/>eſpecially the Prelates of his time: Soul-thieves and murderers, rather than true Miniſters.
<hi>Ministers</hi> ſhall I call them in <hi>Divinity? monſters</hi> they are in <hi>Morality. Beaſts in mens ſhapes, rather than Miniſters, which ought to bee the beſt of men.</hi> Oh the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of ſin! the betraying of our Saviour's intereſſe! and the blood of immortall ſouls, that will bee requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at your hands! I ſay <hi>at your hands,</hi> if any ſuch are here. What I thou that teacheſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf? Art a light to them that ſit in darkneſs, and yet the light that is in thee is but dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Tell'ſt others of a narrow way to heaven, and yet art treading thy ſelf the broad way to hell? Preſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt humility, holineſſe, and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-mindedneſſe in the Pulpit, and there is nought but pride, profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, coveteouſneſſe, or contention in thy practice? Warn'ſt others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ſinne, and againſt all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of ſinne, and to adorn the doctrine of God our Saviour in all things, as ever they would enjoy <pb n="70" facs="tcp:171453:54"/>him or heaven; and yet walkeſt thy ſelf, as if there were neither ſin, nor ſuffering, God or Goſpell, hell or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to be ſhut into, or ſhut out from? And art thou a Miniſter (thinkeſt thou) that Chriſt wil, &amp; Chriſtians muſt own? Oh! how will Chriſt ſhake off ſuch propheſiers in his name, in the open view and proſpect both of men and Angels at the laſt day? and profeſſe unto them, <hi>I never knew you,</hi> i. e. <hi>I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver owned you, Depart from mee yee that work iniquity. Ah wretches! take yee my Covenant into your mouths, and take up my Commiſſion as Miniſters, and yet live like miſcreants?</hi> Verily if there be a furnace of divine vengeance heated one ſeven times more, then uſuall, theſe ſhall fill it: if there be an hotter place in hell than others, theſe ſhall have and howl in it. If you will not receive it from mee, read I pray, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.17. to the end,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 7, 22.23. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 50.15. <hi>Hoſ</hi> 4.6.
<hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20, 21. O Chriſtians, have you no tears left for theſe men? no bowels of pity and compaſſion? eſpecially when the Church of Chriſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo concerned in them? Alas! without <pb n="71" facs="tcp:171453:54"/>eminent repentance, there remains no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>wo, wo, wo,</hi> for them. For wrath and aſtoniſhment, for horrour and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement, for blackneſſe and chains under darkneſs are ſuch reſerved, <hi>for ever and ever. Such Angels,</hi> whoſoever ſcape, <hi>ſhall be ſure to be tormented among the damned Devills.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sect. 2. <hi>Let us mourn for uncommiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Miniſters. Miniſters!</hi> do I mean ſuch? nay rather they are <hi>buſie-bodies in other mens matters.</hi> Miniſters by intruſion they are, and equivocally; but not by inveſtiture not properly; if <hi>in title,</hi> yet not in
<hi>truth.</hi> Their judgement pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds of themſelves, and uſually are in judgement and for deſtruction to the ſheep; not for the preſervation, but for the perdition of the ſouls that are led by, and liſten to them; witneſſe thoſe <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 14.14, 15, 16. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 27.25.
2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>&amp;c. So uſuall hath it been, for ſelf-Miniſters, to be ſoul mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers,</hi> Nor do the Prophets onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim ſuch for <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> who run, and God ne're ſent them with that meſſage; but ſuch likewiſe who run and God never ſent the men: or if you will, <pb n="72" facs="tcp:171453:55"/>
                  <hi>ſuch who propheſied &amp; God never ſent them,
<note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 23.21. and 14.14.15.</note> aswel as thoſe who propheſied what God never ſpoke to them.</hi> It is true that ordinarily both theſe met in one and the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. And is it not as true as familiar and frequent in our times? It never was (I am apt to think) more uſuall in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> than now it is in <hi>England,</hi> that <hi>ſuch who propheſie without deſignation or warrant from God, propheſie the deceit of their own hearts, inſtead of the Word of God.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ezek. 13.1, 2, 3, 17. Jer. 14.1. &amp;
23.16, 26.</note> And are not ſuch, think we, for a lamentation? yea, and let them be for a lamentation. Oh friends! theſe, theſe are they, that have been ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of by God, <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 23.21, 32. ſo much cautioned to the godly, <hi>Jer.</hi> 29. <hi>ver</hi> 8, 9. So much the curſe of that Prince, who hath given them counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.
<hi>verſe</hi> 1. <hi>ad</hi> 37. and have ſo miſerably cheated, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niciouſly corrupted the people that have repoſed confidence, or taken com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie in them,
<hi>Ezekiel</hi> 13. <hi>verſe</hi> 4. <hi>ad</hi> 17. Oh Chriſtians! as there were falſe Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s alſo among the people, hath not Chriſt foretold
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 7.15. &amp; 24.23, 24, 25, 26. 2 Pet. 2.1. &amp;c. 1 Joh. 4.1.</note> that <hi>there ſhall bee falſe teachers <pb n="73" facs="tcp:171453:55"/>among you?</hi> and have not our eyes ſeen them? men of the ſame cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, and of the ſame cariage, which he foretold? and have not the ſame ſad conſequences been found among us, who have read their <hi>deſcription deluſions, and dreadfull iſſues</hi> in the 2
<hi>Pet.</hi> 2. and in the Epiſtle of <hi>Jude?</hi> Sirs, that our ſouls could weep in ſecret for them! and for the Church, Cauſe and Covenant of our God, that ſuffer through and by them! And as for you the Prophets and Miniſters of God, let me ſay to every one of you from the Lord, what was ſometime ſaid unto <hi>Ezekiel. Son of man, propheſie againſt the Prophets of Iſrael</hi> (Saith he, of <hi>England</hi> ſay I, to you)
<hi>that propheſie, &amp; ſay unto them that propheſie out of their own hearts: Hear ye the word of the Lord Thus ſaith the Lord God Wo unto the fooliſh Prophets, that follow their own ſpirit, and have ſeen nothing &amp;c.</hi> Ezek. 13.1, 2, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Uſe 2. Of holy caution, Is it ſo that ſuch who are to teach authoritatively in the Church muſt be both qualified for the Office, and have the Office commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them? I have this to beſeech and beg, to command and charge you, from <pb n="74" facs="tcp:171453:56"/>and by the Lord. Take heed, Oh! take heed, of adventuring upon publick au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritative teaching in his Church, till you have both of theſe; parts and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, qualifications and commiſſion gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Sect. 1. <hi>Do not adventure upon this Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice without qualfications.</hi> This is ſuch an Office, that (what head is ſo able! What heart is ſo accurate and honeſt!) who is equall to it? If the Apoſtle cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; who is equall or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient? 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16. What muſt we do who are not more ſhort of his Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, than we are of his abilities? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>no life can be too good, no learning can be too great for the Miniſtry, nay or good or great enough.</hi> A Paſtor among his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, like <hi>Saul</hi> among his ſubjects, ſhould be higher at leaſt by head and ſhouldiers both for fidelity and for ability, for ſoundneſſe of apprehenſions, for ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of affections and for ſincerity and unbiaſtneſſe in all his actions. Like <hi>Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, one that hath prepared his heart to ſeek the law of the Lord, and to do it, and to teach in Iſrael ſtatutes and judgments,</hi> Ezra 7.10. <hi>Who-ever may be blame-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:171453:56"/>a biſhop muſt be blameleſſe as the Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard of God.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 3.2. as the Apoſtle inculcateth twice together.
<hi>Tit.</hi> 1.6, 7. Nor is it enough that he be <hi>good really</hi> but he muſt have a <hi>good report;</hi> and this not only of them that are within, but of them likewiſe, which are without. 1 Tim. 3.7. But becauſe 'tis not life, ſo much as learning, which is now adays made the matter of queſtion, if not of contumely and contention: Let mee have the liberty to leave my ſenſe in this likewiſe. And I beſeech you, let not pride, let not prejudice, let not precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy, or what-ever elſe, ſhut up your ears, or ſtop your hearts againſt it. Oh! <hi>never think that you are apt to be teachers of others, unleſſe you are able to teach others alſo.</hi> Know that ſuch a one had need be full of goodneſſe, and filled with all knowledg, who is fit (eſpecially of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice) to admoniſh others
<hi>Rom.</hi> 15.14. Full of judgment and of might, <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.8 He had need with <hi>Ezra,</hi> be a ready ſcribe in the Law of God, <hi>Ezra</hi>
7.6. a ſcribe inſtructed to the Kingdom of God <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 13.52. one of pickt and choice abilities and experience, worth and wiſdome; a <pb n="76" facs="tcp:171453:57"/>meſſenger, and interpreter one among a thouſand, <hi>Job</hi> 33.23. an able Miniſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the New Teſtament, 2
<hi>Cor</hi> 3.6.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">'Well may ſuch be reckoned by ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Apoſtle among the
<hi>Impoſtors</hi> of the laſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> times, who <hi>underſtand not,
<note n="a" place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 1. <hi>cum</hi> 12.</note> but ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> willingly ignorant</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.8.</note> of which ſort are they that creep into houſes, and lead captive ſilly women laden with ſins, led away of divers luſts, ever learning, and never able to come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the truth 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6.7. But never were, or ſhall they be reputed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Paſtors</hi> of the laſt times; for theſe are to hold faſt the faithful word as they have been taught, and are able by ſound doctrine both to exhort and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the gain-ſayers <hi>Tit.</hi>
1.9. Theſe caſt not off, but continue in the thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which they have learned and been aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.14.</q> 
                  <hi>A good Miniſter of Chriſt is one nouriſhed up in the words of faith, and of good doctrine whereunto hee hath attained.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6 True it is, that wee are fallen among men and times, that diſcourage, diſſuade and diſgrace learning: but let not that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter us, who are not (through mercy) <pb n="77" facs="tcp:171453:57"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut ſuch, that on the other hand, quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, cheriſh, countenance it, and <hi>ſpeak
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mfortably unto all the Levites that teach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he good knowledg of the Lord.</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Chro. 30. 22.</note> It's true, ſome would have us Preachers like <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>boams Prieſts,</hi> only of the loweſt of the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eople. 1 <hi>King.</hi>
12.31. at leaſt, <hi>for lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ature</hi> (not to mention <hi>livelyhood.</hi>) And well may ſuch indeed paſſe for the <hi>Priests of Jeroboam,</hi> for (with me 'tis
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eyond doubt) they are not the <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hers of Jeſus,</hi> i.e. by his allowance and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ppointment. No; Chriſtians, his are <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pproved workmen, that need not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed, rightly dividing the word of truth,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Tim</hi> 2.15. <hi>The Pastors after his heart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e ſuch, as ſhall</hi> (and therefore can) <hi>feed
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is People with knowledg and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</hi> Jer. 3.15. <hi>not blind ſeers, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ant watch-men, or Shepherds that can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot underſtand.</hi> Iſai. Chap. 56. verſe 10, 11. I do not ſay, but you may be <hi>good men,</hi> and have but little or no learning; but I dare not ſay, you will make <hi>good Miniſters</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out learning; for how ſhould you? I pray conſider.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:171453:58"/>
               <p>N. 1. <hi>Will not your relations to God ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> upon you for learning?</hi> He imploys none but the <hi>wiſe and faithfull</hi> to be his <hi>Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards. Mat.</hi> 13.52. How can you bee his <hi>mouth?</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Jer. 15.19.</note> his
<hi>meſſengers?</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Iſa. 42.19.</note> or the <hi>men of God</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.11.</note> elſe, who are to make known the myſteries of his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell? If you are the mouth of God, let us hear you <hi>ſpeak as the Oracles of God.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet. Chapter</hi> 4.
<hi>verſe</hi> 11. Who do expect <hi>a proof of Chriſt ſpeaking in and by you</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">2 Cor. 13.3.</note> if you are <hi>the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> Let us ſee that <hi>your lips do preſerve knowledg, that men may find the law at your mouth Malac.</hi> Chapter 2. verſe 7. And if you are <hi>men of God,</hi> make us at leaſt ſome way ſenſible, that <hi>you are furniſhed with inſtructions to every good work.</hi> 2 Tim. Chap. 3 verſe 17.</p>
               <p>N. 2.
<note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 5.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Will not your relations to the people call upon you for learning?</hi> Theſe you ought to
<hi>warn and teach in all wiſedom,
<note n="i" place="margin">Iſa. 9.16</note> Col.</hi> 1.28.
<note n="k" place="margin">Mat 13.52.</note> How ſhall you be their <hi>lights?</hi> their <hi>leaders,</hi> and <hi>inſtructors elſe unto the Kingdom of God? If you are blind lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the blind, both ſhall fall into the</hi> 
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:171453:58"/>ditch, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.14. And a dreadfull thing it will b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for you, if <hi>God's people are deſtroyed for lack of knowledge</hi> in you,
<hi>Hoſ</hi> 4.6. <hi>Your lips ſhould preſerve know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> for the people, as a publick ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe; and <hi>they muſt ſeek the law at your mouth, Mal.</hi> 2.7. If there ariſe matters too hard for them, they muſt ariſe and ask you, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8. <hi>ad</hi> 12. <hi>Ezek.</hi>
44.24. And how ſhall you teach them, if ye are yet to learn the Oracles of God your ſelves? <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Thou that teacheſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle? <hi>Rom.</hi>
2.12.</p>
               <p>N. 3. <hi>Will not the requiſites and duties of your office call upon you for learning?</hi> Surely <hi>the Law ſhould not periſh from the Prieſt, nor counſel from the wiſe, nor the Word from the Prophet, Jer.</hi> 18.18. Men may declaim humane or School-learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very confidently; but whereunto will a Miniſter's duty ariſe, unleſs he be furniſhed with ſome competency there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? How ſhall hee <hi>convince gain ſayers</hi> without it,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſhutting them up in their argum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nts and anſwers? or ſtop the mouths of the learned adverſaries, who fly either to the originall texts, or to <pb n="80" facs="tcp:171453:59"/>thoſe orderly contextures of truth, which have received the allowance and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent both of teachers and Chriſtians, to ſtand as maximes of unqueſtionable truths? Beſides how ſhall he rightly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the word of truth elſe, 2
<hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. or reconcile the Scriptures which ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly differ, if he hath no acquaintance with Logick, Rhetorick, or Grammar? Again, how ſhall he reveal the ſenſe of Scriptures entirely, and cauſe the people to underſtand the reading? <hi>Nehemi.</hi> 8. <hi>ver.</hi> 7, 8. Eſpecially, ſince there are ſo many riddles
<note n="l)" place="margin">Ezek. 17 2.</note> and dark ſayings
<note n="m)" place="margin">Pſ. 78.2.</note> in them, and all expoſitions of, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations from them, are to bear ſuch exact accord to, and to be examined by the originall, which the Holy Ghoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired. Nay, or how ſhall he ſo much as read the Scriptures intelligently without ſome humane teachings and learning? Deliver this Bible to one that is not at all learned, ſaying, read this I pray you, and muſt he not ſay I cannot, for I am not learned! <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.12, Had wee to do with no more then <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles; how many things muſt be acknowledged in them, both hard to be underſtood, and <pb n="81" facs="tcp:171453:59"/>hard to be utterred?
<note n="n)" place="margin">Heb. 5.11.</note> But what do the unlearned and unſtable? Let <hi>Peter</hi> tell you: They wreſt them, as they do alſo the other Scriptures, <hi>unto their own deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> 2
<hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. 'Tis in vain to tell me that Jeſus Chriſt was not learned. For doth not he himſelf aſſure me otherwiſe? <hi>The Lord God hath given me the tongue of the learned, and opened mine ear to hear as the learned, Iſa.</hi> 50.4. And do not his auditors aſſure me the ſame too? <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.54, 55. <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.15. Say you the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were not learned? and as for the Prophets how illitterate were they! But ſirs, do the Scriptures ſay the ſame like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe? Indeed, was <hi>Moſes</hi> ſuch an one, who was learned in all the wiſedom of the Egyptians?
<hi>Act.</hi> 7.22. or was <hi>Daniel,</hi> to whom God had given skill in all learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and wiſedom? <hi>Dan.</hi> 1.17. or was <hi>Paul</hi> that was brought up at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel, Act.</hi> 23.5. and was ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently verſed both in humane learning
<note n="o)" place="margin">Tit. 1.22 Act. 17.28</note> and divine, that <hi>Feſtus</hi> thinks <hi>much learning had made him even mad? Act.</hi> 26.24. Again, were <hi>Samuel, Elijah,</hi> or <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſo unlearned, who had ſo many pupills, and bred up ſo many ſcholars, which
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:171453:60"/>were called ſons of the Prophets, at <hi>Nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth, Bethel, Jericho,</hi> and <hi>Gilgall,</hi> which were in this reſpect little other than Univerſities and Schools of learning? 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.19, 20. 2
<hi>Kings</hi> 2.2 3, 5, 12. and 4.38. as we read of a Colledge at
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi> likewiſe, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.22. and 2 <hi>Kings</hi>
22.14. True it is, that grace cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led many ſuch to be Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who were unlearned: but then the ſame grace which called, did by and by qualify the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with learning, that they were, as <hi>Micah</hi> ſaith of himſelf, <hi>full of power by the Spirit of the Lord, and of judgment, and of might, Micah</hi> 3.8. If they had not learning by outward education, they had learning by inward inſpiration, and ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. If they had not acquired learning, <hi>i. e.</hi> by their own ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, they had (which is better) infuſed learning by the Spirit of grace. The Spirit did ſtill make an extraordinary ſupply of learning from himſelf, unto ſuch as were allowed of him in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, that were without an ordinary ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply thereof by Schools of learning. To one was given ſaith
<hi>Paul,</hi> by the Spirit <pb n="83" facs="tcp:171453:60"/>
                  <hi>the word of wiſedom, to another the word of knowledg by the ſame Spirit, to another prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, to another diſcerning of ſpirits, to another diverſe kinds of tongues, to another the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of tongues; all which were wrought by the ſelf-ſame Spirit,</hi> 1 Cor. 128, 10.11.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sect. <hi>Do not adventure upon publick authoritative teaching in the Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a commiſſion.</hi> If you expect the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, acceptance, allowance, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of Chriſt; Oh! do not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture upon it, without authority firſt given you of Chriſt. If affectation, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varice, if ambition, or whatever elſe it be, ſhall be putting you on; let the aw of this truth of God, &amp; your accounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs to the God of truth prepo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derate &amp; ſtay you back; as ever you would anſwer it to Chriſt, to his Church, or to your own Conſciences another day Sirs, the time is coming, when a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zards ſhall bee pluck'd off, and what were your aims by, what your abilities for, and why you declined author<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zing to the Miniſtry ſhall bee produced in open Court, and conſcience ſhall bee put to it (will you nill you) to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer ſuch interrogatories as theſe are: <pb n="84" facs="tcp:171453:61"/>Who made you a teacher in Iſrael? who required this at your hands? who gave you this authority?
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſirs, will not this bee a ſad indictment from the Lord in that day? I did not ſend theſe Prophets, theſe preachers, yet they ran; I have not ſpoken to them yet they propheſied. Well; is it ſo, that ſuch teachers muſt have a commiſſion as well as qualifications from our Lord Jeſus Chriſt? Oh! that ſuch among us, who exerciſe the Miniſtry, enjoy the maintenance, and expect the reverence of Miniſters, yet never entred by the door of Ordination upon the diſcharge of this Office, but have climbed up ſome other way, would ſeriouſly lay it to heart! What? is the Miniſtry an Office? and the external committing of the Miniſtry unto men God's Ordinance? how is it then, that ſuch do (that I ſay not that ſuch da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e) ordinarily exerciſe the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, as to the preaching part, who never were, and perhaps never will be, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did deſign, nor do now deſire to be ſolemnly ſet apart to the Miniſtry? Conſider I pray you theſe two things. 1. That to do the proper work of a <pb n="85" facs="tcp:171453:61"/>Miniſter or Officer of God cannot bee ſafe. 2. To do the preaching work of a Miniſter cannot but be ſinfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>N.</hi> 1. To do the proper work of a Miniſter or Officer of God cannot bee ſafe, without his ordination or appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereunto. Men may paſſe it by, it is true, but God will not put it up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed. The holieſt pretexts of <hi>Korah</hi> and his complices will not help them, if they ſeek the Prieſthood. <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.3.10, 31.32, 33. God is ſo far from bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing withit in common men, that he would at no hand take it from the chiefeſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate: witneſſe <hi>Sauls</hi> loſſe of the Kingdome for it, though burdened then with ſo great ſtraits 1 <hi>Sam.</hi>
13 8 to 15 &amp; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziahs</hi> leaproſie to the day of his death for it, though (before this) hee had been bleſſed with ſo great ſucceſſe. 2
<hi>Chron.</hi> 26.16 to 22. And now beloved, is not ordinary authoritative teaching in the Church the proper work of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Chriſt? Yea; what is, if this benot? Wherefore or whereunto is a Miniſter or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained elſe, if not to be a Preacher and Teacher of the Church in faith and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity? 1
<hi>Tim.</hi> 2.7. wherefore worthy of <pb n="86" facs="tcp:171453:62"/>double honour elſe, if not for labouring in the word &amp; doctrine, which eminently beſpeaketh preaching? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. Wherefore is the Goſpell and this Office committed to him elſe, if not for mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſting the word through preaching? <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.3. yea indeed, not ſo much to baptize as to preach. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17. Beloved, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis we are allowed of God to be put in truſt with the Goſpel, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2, 4. ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are we appointed of God to this truſt in the Goſpel, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.11. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and thereunto it is that we are ſo adjured and called upon God in the Goſpell. I charge thee before God and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall judg the quick and the dead at his appearing, and his Kingdom; preach the word, be inſtant inſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, out of ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c 2 <hi>Tim.</hi>
4.1, 2.
<q rend="margQuotes">'Sirs, is there any proper act of a Goſpel-Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter? If there be not, why do you not plainly tell us, there is no ſuch Officer left us? If there be, may not preaching put in as fair and full, yea a fairer and fuller claim than any? Say you, the adminiſtration of the Sacraments is al proper act of this Officer? Be it ſo but conſider I beſeech you, whether preaching may not put in for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedence
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:171453:62"/>thereunto? Are Goſpell-Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters more eminently, or more expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid, either to be commiſſioned to be Miniſters, for that act then for this? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.7. or more commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their miniſtry by that act, than by this? 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. or more to bee counted of with reſpect to their mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, for that act, than for this? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12, 13. or are we more often, or more openly circum-ſcribed, or deſcribed, as the Miniſters of the Lord by that, than by this? <hi>ibid</hi> &amp; <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7. Or are wee more concerned, and commanded, and charged to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon that act of our Miniſtery, than this? <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.7, 8. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13, 14,
15, 16. Sure I am, though I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude not the adminiſtration of the Sacraments from being a proper act of an Office-Miniſter, and one of thoſe purpoſes and ayms, why God will have men put into the Miniſtry; yet prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Goſpell is with more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant frequency expreſſed among the acts of Miniſters, and with more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant fulneſs evinced to be the aym of God by the Miniſtry. If you have but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verly read the Scriptures, yet you cannot
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:171453:63"/>but obſerve this. With what conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy therefore to ſound reaſon or Scripture-revelation the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Sacraments ſhall be received to bee the Proper act of a Miniſter of Chriſt: and authoritative teaching re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rejected mean-while, judge ye?</q> And if it be (as it is proved to be) the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per act of a Miniſter thus to preach au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatively; what an adventure you run, what an attempt you ruſh upon, Oh that you may attend in time, who Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily diſcharg this part of our Office without Ordination thereunto.</p>
               <p>N. 2. <hi>Todo the preaching work of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ordinarily, without Ordination can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be ſinfull.</hi> What though we yeeld that there may be an eſſay without it for tryal of qualifications? wil it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be an excuſe for ſuch who make it a trade or courſe? or becauſe the ſons of the Prophets may be called thereunto occaſionally? will it therefore be a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert for him who is exerciſed therein or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily? Can you ſo forget the prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, precepts, precedents and pregnant characters &amp; titles of preachers mentioned formerly. *Is it not ſinful for an unofficed <pb n="89" facs="tcp:171453:63"/>perſon to baptize? Conſult elſe the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes between Papiſts and Proteſtants about midwives baptiſme. And can that be ſinfull for you, yet preaching ſinleſſe? When both theſe are preſcribed in the ſame commiſſion, and preaching hath the precedence; not onely in the order of words there, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worth and eminency elſe-where, as the more notable end, and nobler er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand why we were ſent forth not to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, as our Apoſtle ſaith, but to preach the Goſpel, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17. <hi>i.e.</hi> not ſo much to that as to this. But more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee I beſeech you, whether this ſin tends to theſe three things at leaſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>To the vacating of this Goſpel-Officer,</hi> as to this act at leaſt, of preaching. For if this bee a common operation, what needs a peculiar officer for it? If it may bee, nay muſt bee (for ſo far ſome carry it) the work of every other man, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for abilities to preach, and to lay them out in preaching; what need we as to this purpoſe of an office-Miniſter? Is there a ſpeciall officer for the common work of every particular member in the body civil, military, or naturall? If not
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:171453:64"/>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> there, why here I pray you? Well: muſt we have none to teach authoritatively and by office in the Churches? you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not I ſuppoſe ſhut out the light of ſo many Scriptures, as you have ſeen and heard to ſpeak the contrary. Muſt we? how then (beloved) can authoritative teaching be every ones imployment? We have no ſpeciall organ in the body for feeling, that is the common work of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very member, but we have for fight, for ſmell, taſte, and hearing,
<q rend="margQuotes">'What it is with others I know not, but a thing of ſad remark and reſentment it is with me; that ſo many of thoſe, who at firſt have contended for no more than that unofficed men may preach, have at length caſt off the office of preachers, and therewith caſt out all the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Churches of our deareſt Jeſus.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>To the violating of Goſpel-order.</hi> For what is more openly delivered here, than that every one do his own buſineſs, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying to bee quiet, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.11. That as the Lord hath called every one, ſo hee walk and abide in the ſame calling wherein he was called,
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.17, 20. <pb n="91" facs="tcp:171453:64"/>
                  <hi>That no one think more highly of himſelf than he ought to think, but ſoberly, according as God hath dealt to every man the meaſure of faith,</hi> Rom. 12.3. And that every member keep to his own place in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; <hi>God having ſet the members in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, every one of them, as it hath pleaſed him,</hi> 1 Cor. 12, 18, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>To uſurpation upon the Goſpel-Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi> For who reads not, that they have rule over you, and muſt bee ſo remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, who have ſpoken to you the Word of the Lord? <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7. That ſuch as are to admoniſh you from the Lord, have authority, and are over you in the Lord? 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12. and muſt be eſteemed very highly in love by you for their work ſake, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. If gifted brethren are to labour in the Word and doctrine, to preach or teach authoritatively in the Churches; the Churches muſt then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them reverence. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. yea, &amp; pay them maintenance: for what hath God more cleerly ordained, than that they who preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14. and that he that is taught in the Word communicate to him that teacheth in all good things? <hi>Gal.</hi> 6, 6.
<q rend="margQuotes">'But I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear <pb n="92" facs="tcp:171453:65"/>any longer to rub upon this ſoar; truſting thorow grace, that the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiniſm produced by this liberty of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying (as it is miſnamed) will at length awaken all the people of God and preachers of the Goſpell to a juſt averia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion from, &amp; abhorrence of it.</q> And I no way doubt but ſuch Proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts at length, as run to &amp; fro, preaching the dreams &amp; deluſions of their own hearts, ſhall be aſhamed every one of his viſion which he hath propeſied, neither ſhal they wear any long<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r a rough garment to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>i.e.</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, who commonly wore ſuch garments. 2 King. 1.8 Iſai. 20.2. Mat.
3.4. ſe <hi>Hut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chenſon</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the place</note> But he ſhall ſay, I am no Prophet, I am an husband man: for man taught me to keep cattell from my youth <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.4, 5 As for you brethren and beloved who take your ſelvs to be apt and able, inwardly called and competently qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ach others in the Church, why ſhould not this Office be committed to you, that you may with peace to you, with profit to others, and without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation to God authoritatively teach others? Yea, and let me intreat and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage you by our Lord Jeſus; as ever you would have his preſence with you, his protection and gracious providence
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:171453:65"/>over you, his power aiding, and his grace proſpering you; do not exerciſe the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry ordinarily, without or before en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance thereinto by Ordination. Oh! be not ſo averſe to Chriſts honour, the Churches happineſſe, &amp; your own com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort I but if you are indeed qualified for the Miniſtry, ſee that you have the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry committed to you. Sirs, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſhould your proving for the Miniſtery ſeem ſo dreadfull? or putting into the Miniſtery ſeem no more defirable to you who profeſſe, that this one act of the Miniſtry is ſo delicious and dear unto you? If your aims are right and abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties reall, why there ſhould be ſuch an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation from tryal, I know not. Sure I am, you ſhould be firſt proved, and then, and not till then uſe the Office of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, being found blameleſſe
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.10. <hi>cum</hi> ver. 1, &amp;c.</note> If you are not averſe from, nor affraid of triall, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit your ſelvs, and acquaint us where your exception<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lye, and put not ſuch a ſtumbling block in your brethrens way. Why there ſhould be ſo much loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or averſneſſe to Ordination, if there be ſo much love of, and abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for the office, as is pretended, I muſt profeſs I ſee not.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:171453:66"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Do you tell mee, the Apoſtle ſaith, ye may all propheſie one by one? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.31. <hi>Anſw.</hi> True; all ye that are Prophets, of whom he is now ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 29, 32, <hi>verſes.</hi> He ſaith not all ye people.
<q rend="margQuotes">'One whole ſex are prohibited, 34,
35, <hi>verſes,</hi> and for the other, what leſs than this ſpeaks he? Are all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.29. <hi>i. e.</hi> all are not, Where doth the Scripture tell you of unofficed Prophets? men that never were, nor never will be put into office, yet ordinarily did and might perform this act of office? See you not how di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct the mention is of the Prophet and righteous man? <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.42. and how frequently the Prophet is delivered in upon the Catalogue of Church-Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, even in this ſame Epiſtle? 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object Eldad and Medad</hi> (ſay you) <hi>do propheſie in the Camp.</hi> Numb. 11.27. <hi>Anſw.</hi> True; and who would not have wiſhed with <hi>Moſes</hi> in the ſame caſe? would God all the Lord's people were Prophets! But, Lo, when was it? not til the Lord took off the Spirit that was upon <hi>Moſes,</hi> and it reſted upon them, <hi>ver.</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:171453:66"/>26.
<q rend="margQuotes">'And who were they? Of them that were written, but went not out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Tabernacle, <hi>ver.</hi> 26. <hi>i. e.</hi> of the Seventy Elders (officers of Iſrael) whom God commands
<hi>Moſes</hi> to bring thither, and covenants to put upon them of his Spirit, <hi>ver.</hi> 16, 17, 18</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But we are all Prieſts unto God,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Anſw.</hi> True; but not all Prophets, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
12.29. The ſame Chriſt who hath made us Prieſts hath made us Kings too, a royall Prieſt-hood, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. We are neither properly, but in a figurative ſenſe onely.
<q rend="margQuotes">'Will not this veſt us with a civill authority to mulct and puniſh? how will that then, to Miniſter publickly or preach?</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But we all ought to be teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of others?
<hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Anſw.</hi> True, even women are not exempted, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd <hi>Titus</hi> 2.3, 4. Yet not in the Churches, how eminently ſoever gifted, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34, 35. Privately and charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively all may, all muſt, as I have ſaid; Oh let your families, friends, and with whom ye walk in fellowſhip witneſſe it, and let the Word of God dwell richly in you to this purpoſe, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. But <pb n="96" facs="tcp:171453:67"/>ought therefore all to teach publickly and authoritatively likewiſe? Nay, here our Apoſtle: Are all teachers, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>ver.</hi> 29. <hi>i. e.</hi> all are not, all ought not, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.29.
<q rend="margQuotes">'Shew us I pray you, where any gifted brother may aſſume autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to himſelf? or where he is allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of our Saviour, as in his name and ſtead, to teach publickly in the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of his ſervants? and where atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is due to him in ſo doing by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment from the Lord? Hath Chriſt ever ſaid to ſuch as he hath to his office-Miniſters? <hi>He that heareth you heareth me, and he that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me, &amp;c.</hi> Luk. 10.16.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But we muſt ſpeak often one to another, rebuke, conſider, comfort, edifie, and exhort one another; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our families, but eſpecially thoſe with whom wee walk in fellowſhip.
<hi>Anſw.</hi> True; do it and ſpare not. No good man or Miniſter durſt diſſwade or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage it. Nay, this wee do command and charge you by the Lord.
<note n="*" place="margin">Mal. 3.16 Levit. 19.17. Heb. 10.24 25. 1 Theſ. 5.11. Heb. 3.13.</note> But what is this to warrant your publick preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Churches of Chriſt? Is there no difference between that and private <pb n="97" facs="tcp:171453:67"/>Chriſtian-converſe &amp; conferences, which grow out of charity and the communion of Saints?
<q rend="margQuotes">'Do you, will you ſay, but that women among you as wel as men are intended by the Apoſtle in thoſe Scriptures, whereto you allude? yet who ſeeth not that women muſt keep ſilence in the Churches? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34. Pray ſhew us from Scripture, where men out of office are enjoined to ſuch publick teaching, or ſo to teach, from which women are precluded?</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Say you as every man hath received the gift, even ſo ſhould wee mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the ſame one to another, as good ſtewards of the manifold grace of God? <hi>Anſw.</hi> True;
<q rend="margQuotes">'But your ſelves wil not ſay (I think) that women are excluded from what this text enjoyneth. Accept this command then in it's greateſt lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, it can import no more than this, if you allow (what I am ſure you muſt, and believe you do) in it's full accord with other Scriptures,</q> that wee mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the gift we have received one to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, every one in his own orb, in his order; Publick Miniſters of the Church, (in which he inſtanceth <hi>ver</hi> 11.) in a
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:171453:68"/>publick and authori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ative way, private members of the Church in a private and charitative way, as did <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilla, Act.</hi> 18.26.
<q rend="margQuotes">'And beyond doubt, thoſe women that laboured with <hi>Paul</hi> in the Goſpel, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.3. for he ſuffered not a woman to teach in the Church, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. And truly otherwiſe, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame ground that you infer from this text, that every one who hath gifts for publick preaching muſt miniſter the ſame publickly? upon the ſame ground with equal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> right and reaſon may ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inter, that this gifted perſon muſt preach publickly, whether the Church approves him gifted, and indulgeth him this liberty or not: (and indeed where that call and compr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bation of the Church hath any foot-ſteps in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which ſome ſpeak of, e're ſuch ſhall exerciſe his gifts, I ſee not) and again, that every man who hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved gifts or abilities to adminiſter the Sacraments, or to abſolv from cenſures, may and muſt miniſter the ſame to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which you do not, dare not grant, nor indeed may without deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the order of the Churches, deſpiſing <pb n="99" facs="tcp:171453:68"/>the Ordinances of Chriſt, and denying the neceſſity of Miniſters by office. And I pray conſider, whether more eminent abilities be needfull for the ordinary miniſtration of Sacraments, than for preaching? and whether you are more evidently excluded by this text, or by any other from ordinary miniſtration of Sacraments than of ſermons? But if you limit this command, according to the liberty which the words afford you, it ſpeaks for us, and againſt you. For what are ſtewards, but men in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice? and in what other notion, is it ever uſed in Scripture, or where? And thus it wil be no more, than this, in the ſenſe of it: That as every man hath received the office (which is by gift frequently underſtood in Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6, 7. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.8.
<hi>cum</hi> 11.) ſo he miniſter, <hi>viz.</hi> according to his truſt and office; which is illuſtrated particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>v.</hi> 11. wherein he diſtinguiſheth theſe officers or ſtewards, into two <hi>ſpecies</hi> or ranks, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as are to ſpeak from Chriſt, and ſuch as are to ſerve in his Church: ſuch as are to be the mouth of God, authoritatively to guide them; <pb n="100" facs="tcp:171453:69"/>and ſuch as are to miniſter, as of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility which God hath given, <hi>i. e.</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops or Presbyters, and Deacons as he frequently elſewhere maketh the diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe he deſcribeth by the moſt eminent acts of their office, and directeth how they ſhall diſcharge them.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Why? they that were ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered abroad went every where preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Word? <hi>Acts</hi> 8.4. True, but who were they? If you ſay men out of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, let us hear your proof, the onely particular man therewith mentioned is <hi>Philip, ver.</hi> 5. who was e're this ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<hi>Chap.</hi> 6.5, 6. and was an Evangeliſt <hi>Chap.</hi> 21.8 Again, when did they it? when the Church was all ſcattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, which was at
<hi>Jeruſalem, verſe</hi> 1. And is there no difference between prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching under the ſcattering of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and during their ſettlement?
<q rend="margQuotes">'Though I think that the univerſal term [all] <hi>ver.</hi> 1. doth rather intend all the Miniſters of that Church, except the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, than all the members. For why, or where ſhould the Apoſtles have ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if all theſe had been ſcattered
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:171453:69"/>abroad? Or how could <hi>Saul</hi> have been ſtil making havock of the Churchthere, haling men and women to priſons, <hi>v.</hi> 3. which is another probability that they were onely men in office, who went thus preaching to and fro, to which you may add the pregnancy of the expreſſion, which <hi>Luk,</hi> maketh uſe of <hi>verſe</hi> 4 <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which this Evangeliſt hath ſo often and onely uſed of preachers by office, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.4. and 8.12. and 10.36. <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.1. and 9.6. and
20.1. as the late learned laborious and pious Aſſemblie do animadvert.<note n="*" place="margin">ſee their anſwer to the Reaſ. of the diſſ. brethren, p 30, 31, 32.</note>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">'But we find <hi>Apollos</hi> teaching the way of the Lord diligently, even in the Synagogue? <hi>Act.</hi> 18.25. True, but who was <hi>Apollos?</hi> not onely an ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent man, &amp; mighty in the Scriptures, <hi>verſe</hi> 24. but is expreſly mentioned to be one of the Miniſters by whom the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> believed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
3.5, 6. and in that regard he is owned by <hi>Paul,</hi> as his brother
<hi>Apollos</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.12. and ranked with him &amp; <hi>Pet,</hi>
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. Say you he was not put into office when he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at
<hi>Epheſus, Act.</hi> 18. but how prove you it? Surely the mention of his knowledg <pb n="102" facs="tcp:171453:70"/>only of <hi>John</hi>'s baptiſm, <hi>i. e.</hi> his doctrine and Miniſtry, <hi>ver.</hi> 25, will be too ſlender a proof thereof; eſpecially if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the other characters therewith given him, and the contracted knowledge of the Diſciples of Jeſus, ſome time after their firſt ſending forth, and that <hi>John</hi> had his Diſciples, as well as had Jeſus his. But further ſuppoſe we it: yet what can be more inferred, than we readily grant? <hi>viz.</hi> that that one who purpoſeth the Miniſtry, and is preparatorily quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for it, may give proof of his qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations by preaching ſome ſermons e're his putting into office; into which it is manifeſt that <hi>Apollos</hi> was, if not already put, yet not long after this at <hi>Corinth,</hi> to which he paſſed from <hi>Epheſus ver.</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>cum Ch.</hi> 19.1.</note>
26.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">'Doth not <hi>Jehoſophat</hi> ſend his princes toteach in the Cities of <hi>Judah?</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17, 7. and with them the Prieſts and Levites <hi>v.</hi> 8, and they taught in
<hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, v.</hi> 9. True; So that there is never an unſent teacher. Amemorable and imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble precede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (no doubt) for ſupreme go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours: that the teachings of the Law of the Land and of the Law of the Lord do go together, the Magiſtrates teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="103" facs="tcp:171453:70"/>that, and taking care for, and giving countenance to the Miniſters teaching this. But behold, it is ſo done, as the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Lord and the matters of the Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, are diſtinctly ordered by diſtinct officers, as the ſame <hi>Jehoſophat</hi> appoints <hi>Chap</hi>
19.11. So that it no where appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that the ſecular Lords and Princes did teach the ſame matters, and in the ſame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner, as did the Prieſts &amp; Levites.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>Object.</hi> Say any yet amongſt us? Sir, we have been proved and approved by the Miniſters of Jeſus. Som of us former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, under the power of the Committees; ſome now before the preſent Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers which are intruſted with the inductio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Miniſters. Why ſhould you preſs us to ordination, who can already offer ſo fair and full a plea for the office? <hi>Anſ.</hi> Be it ſo, as you have ſaid in the former part; (though how many have crept in at another door without either proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or approbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I am loth to ſpeak) Surely, as I cannot but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend ſo much care on the part of the civil Magiſtrate, e're he inveſts men with the civil right of enjoying the maintenance, or inducteth them to the exerciſe of the Miniſtry <pb n="104" facs="tcp:171453:71"/>in ſuch a particular pariſh; yet this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering I muſt tell you, will be too nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for you, who expect the doubleho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and execute the office of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt. How ſtrictly you were proved, your ſelves beſt know; but that you were not ſolemnly approved, with prayer, faſting, and impoſition of hands, who knoweth not? If your ſelves will but ask your approvers now, or hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, you will eaſily receive this ready anſwer: That they did not put you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the office of Miniſters; (ſuch kind of ordinations having no patrons (that I know) among men, nor pretexts for it from God, nor ſcarce any conſiſtence with any principles amongſt us what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.) But what they did was to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit and approve you, ſo far as concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, as delegated from the civill Magiſtrate, to the exerciſe and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Miniſtry in ſuch a place. Formerly none might be approved, but ſuch as were already office-Miniſters; at preſent none but ſuch as are (if not actually made Miniſters, yet) apt and able for the Miniſtry; the actuall inveſtiture of men with which <pb n="105" facs="tcp:171453:71"/>Office is not their preſent buiſneſſe. And though whether this inveſtiture be in the power of the Presbytery, or of the people, may not be ſo well accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: Yet that there is ſomething elſe, than the preſent approbation, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king one an Office-Miniſter, is on all hands between thoſe of the presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an and Congregational perſwaſions aſſented to.'</q>
               </p>
               <p>Sirs, may any or all this weigh with you? Or will you yet retain your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices? Let me onely mind you of that of the Apoſtle: That no man think of himſelf, more highly then he ought to think; <hi>Rom.</hi> 12, 3. and renew my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer motion once more to you, and I paſſe to the next uſe. Sirs, are you gifted in earneſt for the Miniſtry? and have you not gilded over your prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching out of Office, with pretexts only? Oh! com, come, try your qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and take up a commiſſion, and ſee whether wee'l not give you the right hand of fellowſhip.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. Of hearty Counſell, wherein I muſt and ſhall be very contract, being ſenſible both of your work, and my own
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:171453:72"/>weakneſs. It ſhall be 1. To you unto whom this office is or ſhall be this day committed. 2. To you over whom God hath or ſhall commit ſuch offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</p>
               <p>Sect. 1. To you unto whom this Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice already is, or ſhall be this day com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. Is it ſo &amp;c. This calleth upon you to do the whole Offic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to you of God, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o to demean your ſelves as thoſe that have this holy Office comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to you of God. 1.
<q rend="margQuotes">'To d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the whole Office that is committed to you. Make full proof of your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 4.5 'Tis (let me tell you) of a vaſt c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mpaſs; doctrinall, diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinary, publick, private, in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, &amp;c. and of a vaſt conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e it h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d never b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en ſo affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionately perſwaded by Chriſt, and ſo awfully preſſed by his Apoſtle, or ſo frequently by both. <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.15, 16, 17. 1
<hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21 <hi>ch</hi> 6.13.14. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. <hi>ad</hi> 6. As ever we would have peace in our own boſomes, or be pure from others blood, let us with-hold nothing from our people, that is profitable for them to know, and proper for us to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate. <pb n="107" facs="tcp:171453:72"/>This will be their crown, and our comfort. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.20, 27, 28. If we would not be counted men but of half-hearts, or would not be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with an half-holineſſe in our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or with an half-heaven for our own perſons, let us do, I pray you, our whole work. It cannot be concealed that wee have in theſe times a great many half-Chriſtians,
<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 26.18.</note> halfe profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; and it muſt be confeſſed, that we have but too many half-miniſters, or half-paſtours, as to the execution of their Office. And ſurely, to me it ſeems not much an inferiour ſoleciſm accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Scripture, to hear of an half-Miniſter, as to hear of an half-Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in grace, or an half-man in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. 2.</q> This calleth upon you ſo to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean your ſelves in the work of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, as thoſe that have the Office com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto you of God.
<q rend="margQuotes">'The man of God, eſpecially in the matters of God, muſt not be or behave himſelf, only after the rate of other men. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.24. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6 11. The ordinary works we perform, ſhould leave a reliſh &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of that ſacred word we preach, &amp; <pb n="108" facs="tcp:171453:73"/>of this ſpiritual Office we are put into. An Sirs! what examples, ſhould wee Paſtours be to our people in (well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigh) every particular! in word, in converſation, in charity, in ſpirit, in faith, in purity, 1 <hi>Iim.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2, 7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5 3. He that hath my word, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t him ſpeak my word faithfully, what is the chaffe to the wheat ſaith the Lord,
<hi>Jer.</hi> 23.28. And oh that we may ſhew our ſelves approved unto God, and workmen that need not to bee aſhamed before men! 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. Say you how ſhould we?</q> 1 Let us do our work con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincingly; convincingly both in regard of others conſciences,
<note n="a" place="margin">Joh. 8.9.</note> and of our own Commiſſion.
<note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.1.</note> Let us do it with au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, like our Saviour, and not as the Scribes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.29. as thoſe that are ful of power, and of judgment, and of might, by the Spirit of the Lord, <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.8. That when we preach, or pray, or cenſure, or comfort, &amp;c. &amp; there cometh in one that believeth not, he may be ſo convinced of us, and judged of us, and the ſecrets of his heart made manifeſt: As that fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down on his face, he may worſhip God, and report that God is in us of a <pb n="109" facs="tcp:171453:73"/>truth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.24, 25.
2. Let us do our work conſcientiouſly and ſincerely; without partiality as to man, and with purpoſes for God.
<q rend="margQuotes">'For why elſe is our Commiſſion?
1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.11, 12 what elſe is God's Command? 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. or what leſſe will be our comfort? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. and muſt be our character, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.17. 1 Be not partial towards men, how ſhall we then prove our ſelves the Miniſters and Stewards of Chriſt? 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 4 1, 2. who muſt give every one their portion of meat in due ſeaſon, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.42. Let us remember God's Covenant with <hi>Levi, Deut.</hi> 33 8, 9. and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand he hath left with us, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi>
5.21. And truly it is worth our moſt ſerious reflections upon our ſelvs, whether, what the Lord ſomtime in way of reproof told the Prieſts, doth not now as particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reach us, in the midd'ſt of ſo many reproches!
<hi>viz.</hi> Therefore have I alſo made you contemptible and baſe before all the people, according as ye have not kept my ways, but have been parti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l in my law, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.9. Again, 2. Let all our purpoſes center in God. Wee are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to bee called his Officers, who are careleſſe of his honour, and <pb n="110" facs="tcp:171453:74"/>unworthy that hee ſhould have a care of ours, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. Sirs, let us not preach our ſelves, but Jeſus the Lord,</q> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi>
4.5. As of ſincerity, as of God, in the ſight of God, ſo let us ſpeak in Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.17. What I would we pleaſe men? how are we then the ſervants of Chriſt? <hi>Col</hi> 1.10. As we are allowed of God, to be put in truſt with the Goſpel, even ſo let us ſpeak not as pleaſing men, but God, who trieth our hearts, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4. 3. Let us do our work couragiouſly &amp; ſtrenuouſly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deſpondency or ſhrinking, without dejection or ſinking. If God's Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and concurrence will not bear up our hearts, and bear us up thorow hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, I know not what will. A priſoner with theſe at the bar is able to face and fright a Judge upon the bench, <hi>Act.</hi> 24.25.
<q rend="margQuotes">'Were we Embaſſadours in bonds, yet we ought to ſpeak boldly, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. Such is the perſon we ſuſtain, and the place we ſtand in. What ſhould baulk or brow-beat us, who have ſuch an authority to warrant us, and ſuch almightineſſe with us, to work all our works in us and for us? 2
<hi>Tim.</hi> 1.11, 12. Were wee private men, or went wee <pb n="111" facs="tcp:171453:74"/> but upon a private meſſage, well might our hearts m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ditate terrors. But being Officers of Chriſt, and ſuch as hee will own to the worlds end, nor bonds, nor blood, or death ſhould move us, <hi>Act</hi> 20.23, 24, and 21.13 A few b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g looks, or bitter words, or biting ſcoffs are ſorry bug-bears to daunt a Commiſſion-offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of Jeſus; to whom is given all pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er both in heaven and earth, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lls us for our encouragement, <hi>Mat</hi> 28.18, 19, 20. How would we have born to have ſtood at the bar?
<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 25.6, 7</note> or have ſate in the ſtocks?
<note n="d" place="margin">c. 16.23, 24, 25.</note> or have been ſcourged at the Whipping-poaſt
<note n="e" place="margin">2 Cor. 11.24.</note> with our predeceſſors? yet were they bold in our God, to ſpeak the Goſpell of God, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h much contention 1
<hi>Iheſ.</hi> 2.4. and waxed the bolder, by their own and others bounds,</q>
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.29. 4 Let us do our Miniſteriall work carefully and diligently: neither liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to our own idleneſſe, nor led away of other intanglements. Oh the weight of that one Scripture! worthy to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven in letters of gold, upon all our Study-doors, and to be continually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in our hearts. Give attendance <pb n="112" facs="tcp:171453:75"/>to reading, to exhortation, to doctrine: Neglect not the gift that is in thee which was given thee by propheſie, with the laying on of the hands of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Meditate on theſe things, give thy ſelf wholly to them, that thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting may appear <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to all men, in all things, by all means. Take heed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy ſelf &amp; unto your doctrine, continue in them: for in doing this, thou ſhalt both ſave thy ſelf &amp; them that hear thee. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13, 14, 15, 16.
<q rend="margQuotes">'Are we Officers? we muſt wait on our Office: he that tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth on teaching, and he that exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on exhortation.
<hi>Rom.</hi> 12.7.8. Whoſoever have time to ſpare for the toys and vanities of the world, we have none, whoſe time is Chriſts and his Churches, and who are to give our ſelvs wholly to the word. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi>
4.15. Oh how puz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ng and perplexing would ſuch queſtions as theſe be, if Chriſt ſhould put them unto us. Why ſtand ye here (perhaps) all the day idle? We cannot ſay, No man hath hired us. <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.6, 7. <hi>Or what doſt thou here Elijah?</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.9, 13. be we either in the Cave, or in the croud; either <pb n="113" facs="tcp:171453:75"/>weary of our callings, or waſting our time to and fro about lower concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Sirs, are not we the ſouldiers of Chriſt? No man that warreth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangleth himſelf with the affairs of this life, that he may pleaſe him who hath choſen him to be a ſouldier, 2
<hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. Wee have Sanctuary work to attend. 'Twas death for the Prieſts, if they did not abide in the Sanctuary, according to their ſeverall charges, becauſe the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing oyl of the Lord was upon hem: becauſe they were ſolemnly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to this work and office,
<hi>Levit.</hi> 10.7. and 21.11, 12. and 8.35. It is not reaſon that we ſhal leave the Word of the Lord, ſay the Apoſtle, and ſerve tables,
<hi>Act.</hi> 6.2 this was in miniſtring to the bodily neceſſities of the poor. And ſhall we leave the Word of the Lord, and ſerve the times? or be ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring trifles in compariſon of eternity, with the miſcarriage of our peoples ſouls? Oh! let us ſtir up the gift of God that is in us! Had wee nothing to reflect upon, but the laying on of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hands upon us, this might bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to cauſe us to return upon our <pb n="114" facs="tcp:171453:76"/>own hearts often, and to revive and blow up whatſoever is of love or zeal in us, to a vigorous execution of our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. Are wee Officers of Chriſt, and in his Church? Surely wee had need ply our buſineſſe hard.</q> Nor can we (likely) be too buſie in our office, who have (I am ſure) the higheſt charge,
<note n="f" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.1, 2.</note> the heavieſt account,
<note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> the hardeſt work,
<note n="h" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.2, 5. Jer. 1.18, 19</note> and the hotteſt warfare, <hi>(i)</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3, 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. This truth calleth upon you over whom God hath ſet or committed, or ſhall this day commit ſuch officers. This counſelleth you how to eſteem of, and entertain them in exerciſe of their truſt, and execution of their Miniſtry. Say you how? As thoſe that are officers of the Lord, and as over you in the Lord, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12. As thoſe that are appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God to watch for your ſouls, and muſt give an account, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. And therefore how ſhould you ſubmit your ſelves? and obey them, ſo far as they rule over you in the Lord? that they may give up their account with joy, and not with grief; for that is unprofitable for you, as the Apoſtle adds. What though <pb n="115" facs="tcp:171453:76"/>ſuch have been, or now ſhall be outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appointed by men, yet are they allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God to be put in truſt with the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, 1
<hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4. with <hi>Act.</hi> 13.2, 3. Beloved, thoſe who are ordained of men accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to God's Ordinance, are yet God's Officers, God's Miniſters. What elſe doth <hi>Paul</hi> aſſure us of the Elders, or ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Paſtors and Teachers of the Church of <hi>Epheſus?</hi> (which becauſe ordinary, could not be immediately put into of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice:) The Holy Ghoſt made them over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. Or what elſe doth he affirm of thoſe of the Church at <hi>Coloſſe?</hi> In his mention of
<hi>Epaphras;</hi> 'tis, our dear fellow-ſervant, who is for you a faithful Miniſter of Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.7. When hee minds them their duty touching <hi>Archip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> (who was it ſeems none of the moſt circumſpect or conſtant Miniſter) 'tis thus; Say to <hi>Archippus,</hi> take heed to the Miniſtry which thou haſt received in the Lord, that thou fulfill it, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.17. And what other language hear we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<hi>Tychicus? Col.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Tychicus</hi> a beloved brother and a faithful Miniſter, and a fellow-ſervant in the Lord. So <pb n="116" facs="tcp:171453:77"/>far was it from truth, in the pureſt primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times; that they were onely to bee accounted the officers and Miniſters of the Lord, who were immediately put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the office by the Lord. Well then; let a man ſo account of us as of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt, and ſtewards of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of God, 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. I ſay as Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, not of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, not of Antichriſt. I know there is a common reproach rolled upon the Miniſtry in <hi>England,</hi> as if we were no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> limbs of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, Antichriſtian Prieſts &amp;c. So much unbridled are the ſpirits and ſpeech of many, that would ſeem to bee religious, and thereby ſpeak their religion vain.
<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 1.26.</note> But beloved call you thoſe, or can they be Antichriſtian, who have been ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently oppoſed by Antichriſt, and ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently owned by Chriſt; as have been the zealous and ſtrict Miniſtery in <hi>England,</hi> and ſtill are to this day? Oh! how can you more honour, more help up Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt? or hurl more dirt and diſgrace in the face of Jeſus Chriſt? than by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thoſe Miniſters Antichriſtian, who <pb n="117" facs="tcp:171453:77"/>have been and are ſo powerfully able, and ſo proſperouſly uſeful to break the league of ſo many thouſands of ſouls with ſin and death, and to bring them over to the reall and ready imbracements, of the ſervice of God and life eternall?
<q rend="margQuotes">'Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, have not your eyes ſeen, and ears eard of multitudes both of men and women, that have been, and ſtill are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by them, unto Chriſt through the Goſpel? and that are built up in communion with him through their Miniſtry in the Goſpel? Built up, not in aëry ſpeculations and dotage, about queſtions and ſtrifes of words; whereof cometh envy, ſtrife, railings, &amp;c. This is eaſily done indeed (and among us how eminently) by the ſubtilty and zeal of ſeducers, and ſuch as conſent not to wholeſome words, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi>
6.3, 4, 5. But lo, multitudes built up, through the good hand of God upon the gracious Miniſtry in <hi>England,</hi> in the reall abhorrency of ſin, the rich a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointings of the Spirit, in the life of faith, the labour of love, in the power of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, poverty of ſpirit, in heavenlineſs of their minds within, and holineſs of <pb n="118" facs="tcp:171453:78"/>manners without: In a word, to be do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of righteouſneſs, &amp; in the doctrine which is according to godlineſs. Need I cal for Teſtimony to a truth ſo eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in the mouth of more then two or three thouſand witneſſes?
<note n="k" place="margin">2 Cor. 13.1.</note> Need we, as ſome others, may the pious prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to the pious people of England, from it's firſt reformation ſay; Need we, as ſome others, Epiſtles of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation to you? or letters of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation from you? Yee are our Epiſtle writen in our hearts, known and read of all men. Foraſmuch as ye are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly declared to be the Epiſtle of Chriſt, miniſtred by us; written not with ink, but with the ſpirit of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God; not in tables of ſtone, but in fleſhly tables of the heart 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1, 2.3. What is our hope, or joy, or crown of rejoycing? are not even ye, in the preſence of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, at his comming? 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.19. And will you alſo, being led away with the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the wicked, fall from your own ſteadfaſtneſſe? 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17. you of whom we have been ſo affectionately deſirous, as we were willing to have <pb n="119" facs="tcp:171453:78"/>imparted to you, not the Goſpel of God only, but alſo our own ſouls, becauſe ye were dear to us? 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. And will you alſo liſten to their ſcurrulous imputations, who compaſſe us about with words of hatred, and ſay: Come, and let us ſmite them with the tongue (who cannot now ſmite them with the ſword) and let us not give heed to any of their words. <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.18. Why? Sirs, ye are our work in the Lord. If we are not the Miniſters of Chriſt to others, yet doubtleſſe we are unto you, for the ſeal of our miniſtry are ye in the Lord 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
9.1, 2. Say you, ay, but we are antichriſtian? however we cloak it over,</q> or cover it up? But ſirs, upon what reaſon? whence riſeth it? Are we put into the Miniſtry by antichriſt? No, But by inſtruments that are his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and open adverſaries. Do we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote antichriſt by our Miniſtry? Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: This is to pluck him up root and branch, &amp; to prefer Jeſus Chriſt in all his Offices. Are we protected in our miniſtry by antichriſt? Nor this, unleſſe the croa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings of thoſe froggs which come out of his mouth, the contradictions, calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies <pb n="120" facs="tcp:171453:79"/>and comminations of his Prieſts &amp; Jeſuites (which have immixed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with ſeparatiſts of all ſorts) be our ſhield and protection. Have we not been perſecuted in our miniſtry by Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt? Surely yes; what elſe doth the Book of Matyrs atteſt? and the bonds, blood and aſhes of Holy <hi>Bradford, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Rogers,</hi> and the reſt in
<hi>Q. M.</hi> daies? On the other hand. Have not the purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the zealous Miniſters in England been eminently for Chriſt? To exalt his ſalvation, and with the ejection and downfall of that man of fin? Witneſſe elſe both preſſes and Pulpits. Hath not the preſence of Chriſt been eminently with the zealous miniſtry of England? to blaſt the policies, and break the power of Antichriſt, proſpering them in his own work &amp; againſt the wiles &amp; wrath of that wicked one? Speak malice it ſelf &amp; ſpare not. Hath not the power of Chriſt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n eminently active by, and apparent in the zealous Miniſtry of England? Ark others elſe? If I may not appeal to your own conſciencies: whether their ſermons have not fallen like thunder and lightning upon them? and the <pb n="121" facs="tcp:171453:79"/>weapons of their warfare have not been mighty, through God, to the pulling down of ſtrong holds? and pierced even to the dividing aſunder of ſoul &amp; ſpirit? Nay once more, have there not been, and yet are the prints &amp; characters of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt eminently found upon the zealous Miniſters of England? com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them elſe, with theſe Epiſtles to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> and
<hi>Titus.</hi> Sirs, what elſe have been and are their diſpoſitions and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Miniſtry, but ſuch as Chriſt hath propounded? What elſe their deligation to the miniſtry, for the ſubſtance of it, but ſuch as Chriſt hath preſcribed? What elſe the diſcharge of their Minſtry, for the ſcope and main of it, but ſuch as Chriſt hath preſſed? Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in all this for humane infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; for you may not think we ceaſe to be men, when we come to be Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Laſtly what elſe the doctrine which they did and do ſtill miniſter, but ſuch as Chriſt and his Apoſtles preached?
<q rend="margQuotes">'And are we yet Antichriſtian? Whence, or why is it? Do you tel us we were ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Biſhops (at leaſt ſeverall of us) and theſe are antichriſtian? But Sirs,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:171453:80"/>if you can content your ſelves with ſo littlecharity, I muſt, and do count it my duty to labour for more honeſty, than to brand thoſe holy and learned men with being Antichriſtian, who firſt brought us from under the yoak of Antichriſt, and burn'd in flames of Marty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dom, by his cruelty, for the cauſ of Chriſt. Thus did theſe zealous Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops: <hi>Cranmer, Farrer, Latimer, Hooper, Ridley.</hi> And I doubt not but many others ſince would have ſealed the ſame cauſe, upon the ſame call, with their choiceſt blood, whoſe works and writings for piety and againſt Popery, wil ſpeak for them among the living, when you are ſleeping among the dead. Can Satan thus caſt out Satan?
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Mar.</hi> 3.23.</note> or would Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt ſo conſume and caſt out Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt? Well: but ſhould your preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice paſſe; and we ſuppoſe with you, our Engliſh Biſhops to have been all Antichirſtian, yet will you be to ſeek for proof of your ſequele: that all thoſe are Antichriſtian too, who were ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Biſhops: unleſſe you will hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily call your leaſe or land Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, becauſe this was derived from, or <pb n="123" facs="tcp:171453:80"/>that drawn up by a Popiſh Land-lord. Ordination of Presbyters was not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to a biſhop as ſuch only, for he could not ordain a Presbyter, unleſſe himſelf had been ordained a Presbyter. Nor did he ordain any Presbyters ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by himſelf, but ſtil with the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of other Presbyters. The premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes do plainly enough evince, That one Presbyter may aſſiſt in the Ordination of other Presbyters: That ordination by Presbyters is Gods Ordinance: That Miniſters ſo ordained muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged Gods Officers. If therefore this Biſhop, together with other Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, may warrantably ordain in the capacity of a Presbyter, and one ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by him muſt be reputed the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer of Chriſt; with what right, or by what rule ſhall the ſame man ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by this Biſhop be rejected for an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer of Antichriſt? If this Biſhop loveth to have the preheminence, over the other Presbyters in Ordination, &amp; layeth hold upon it by a divine right, (generally they have claimed by an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane only) it is his ſin, but doth no way annul or alter the ſubſtance of this
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:171453:81"/>man's ordination: no more than doth the ſame Biſhops adminiſtration of the Lord's Supper, upon the ſame aims and affectation, adnull this Supper to any pious ſoul. We wel know, he may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully do this (as likewiſe that) in the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of a Presbyter. Say you yet that our Miniſtry in <hi>England</hi> is Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, becauſe our ordmation came from <hi>Rome,</hi> from Antichriſt? If ſo, you may not be offended if I tell you, that this charge is either utterly fall, or very fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacious. Would you attempt the proof of <hi>England's</hi> converſion and Miniſtry to have come originally from <hi>Rome?</hi> you may indeed gratifie the Jeſuites who have been long ſtriving in this ſubject, but with no ſucceſs: But you ſhould do wel firſt to conſult our Engliſh Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clers upon this ſubject,
<note n="*" place="margin">ſee <hi>Fox's Acts and Monumets</hi> book 2 be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, or <hi>Speeds Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory,</hi> or <hi>Fullers Ecl. Hiſtory.</hi>
                     </note> and the juſt conqueſt, which ſome have already got
<note n="*" place="margin">ſee <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hites way to the Church,</hi> ſect. 49.</note> upon this point: and by that time you will eaſily reſolve, that theſe were not from <hi>Rome,</hi> and if you pleaſe to read on, may ſoon inform your ſelf what ſtout champio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s againſt
<hi>Rome's</hi> apoſtacy, have been uſually found among our Engliſh Miniſtry. We do and muſt tell you, that <pb n="125" facs="tcp:171453:81"/>our ordination came from Chriſt, not from <hi>Rome,</hi> not from Antichriſt, though it is true it hath miſerably been conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated by Antichriſt, as what office or ordinance in the Church hath not? Now that we muſt part with an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Chriſt, becauſ it h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th ſomtime been poſſeſſed by, and paſſed to us tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the hands of ſuch, as have ſerved and ſet up Antichriſt, pray ſhew us, who are wholly to ſeek of ſuch a Scripture. Muſt the Jews caſt away the golden veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of Sion, becauſ they had been quafft in, in the literal [the figure of this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall] Babylon? or muſt they not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther carry them back, in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o the Temple in
<hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
                     <note n="n)" place="margin">Ezra 5.14, 15.</note> which was a type of Jeſus. Or did they ceaſe to be the veſſels of the Temple (I know they ceaſed to be veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels in the Temple) while they were carried to Babylon, or were kept there? Farewell all Churches, conſtitutions, and ordinances of Chriſt; if their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us thorow the bold intruſions and invaſions of Antichriſt, may diveſt us. yea, and farewell the offices of Chriſt too, for upon which of theſe hath he not been and ſtil is an uſurper? <pb n="126" facs="tcp:171453:82"/>But bleſſed be God, all the cunning and commixtures of Antichriſt are not able to vacate one conſtitution of Jeſus Chriſt. Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper, notwithſtanding all his uſurpations and additions, have been, and ſtill are, the bleſſed Ordinances of our Lord &amp; Saviour, and ſhal be till the worlds end,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>cum</hi> 20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. we have his ſecurity therefore; and may thence eaſily aſſume the continuance of an office-Miniſtry, for diſpenſing theſe Ordinances, and conſequently of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation likewiſe;
<note n="*" place="margin">ſee theſe things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved before</note> the Scripture preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing this as the onely courſe of putting men into office, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and never promiſing ſuch office-Miniſters ſince the Apoſtles days, as ſhal be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ordination to the Miniſtry. Come then beloved, ſuffer not your ſelves to be detained with ſuch prejudices, or be drawn aſide with ſuch pretexts from the ordained and office-Miniſters of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</q> But receiv ſuch in the Lord with all gladneſs, and hold them in reputation,
<hi>Phil.</hi> 2.29. neither making nor taking up falſe reports againſt them, neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to hear, nor to honour them; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:171453:82"/>remembring what Chriſt hath told you. Hear them, and you hear him; receive them, &amp; you receive him; diſpiſe them, and you deſpiſe him; and if you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe him, you deſpiſe him that ſent him, <hi>Luk</hi> 10.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.40. 'Tis true, there is little other due to us, than what ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous tongues and pens take liberty to load us with, if we be look'd upon as we are in our ſelves; ſinfull men, that may be in this reſpect the leaſt of Saints,
<note n="o)" place="margin">Eph. 3.8.</note> and chiefeſt of ſinners,
<note n="p)" place="margin">1 Tim. 1 15.</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelf. But there is a double honour which is due unto us, if we be look'd upon as labourers in the Word and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as the meſſengers and Miniſters of Jeſus, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. Sirs, as little reſpect as you will for man's, for our own ſake; yet much is due, for the meſſage ſake, for the Miniſteries ſake, for our Maſters ſake. In this regard,
<hi>Paul</hi> tells <hi>Philemon</hi> that he oweth him his very ſelf,
<hi>Phil.</hi> 19. If you enquire of the beſt of Miniſters as men,
<hi>Elias,</hi> one of the loftieſt Prophets is a man of like paſſions,
<hi>Jam.</hi> 5.17. Alas! wee have the ſame Devill to aſſault us, the ſame deceitfull world to allure us, and the ſame deſparately wicked heart
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:171453:83"/>to aſſiſt to them, and betray us. But if you enquire of us as Miniſters, wee are fellow-helpers concerning you, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi>
8.23. overſeers of you, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. that are to rule over you,
<hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7, 17. and are over you in the Lord, 1 <hi>Theſ</hi> 5.12. We are fellow-workers unto the kingdom of God, workers together with God, 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 6.1. Embaſſadours for Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you by us, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. Let me therefore Chriſtians ſay this unto you, eſpecially of the Congregations concerned in thoſe, which are ſolemnly to be ſet apart to the office and work of the Miniſtry this day, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motheus</hi> unto the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> with a very little change, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.10, 11. If <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus,</hi> if theſe come to you, ſee that they may be with you without fear, for they work the work of the Lord, as we alſo do. Let no man therefore deſpiſe them, but conduct them in and out, in the work of the Lord with peace.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <hi>Soli Deo ſit gloria,</hi> Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:171453:83"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
